<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Moral instructions of a father to his son upon his departure for a long voyage: or, An easie way to guide a young man towards all sorts of virtues. With an hundred maximes, Christian and moral.</title>
            <title>Instruction morale d'un père à son fils. English</title>
            <author>Dufour, Philippe Sylvestre, 1622-1687.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 139 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 62 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81791</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2455A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R231963</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99900081</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99900081</idno>
            <idno type="VID">133315</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81791)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 133315)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2513:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Moral instructions of a father to his son upon his departure for a long voyage: or, An easie way to guide a young man towards all sorts of virtues. With an hundred maximes, Christian and moral.</title>
                  <title>Instruction morale d'un père à son fils. English</title>
                  <author>Dufour, Philippe Sylvestre, 1622-1687.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 99, [9] p.;   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for W. Crook, at the Green Dragon withour Temple-Bar, near Devereaux Court,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Du Four is sometimes regarded as a pseudonym of Jacob Spon.</note>
                  <note>A translation of 'Instruction morale d'un père à son fils', first published in 1677.</note>
                  <note>With advertisements bound at end.</note>
                  <note>Formerly Wing D2455.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Maxims --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Young men --  Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:133315:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>MORAL INSTRUCTIONS OF A FATHER TO <hi>His Son,</hi> UPON HIS Departure for a long VOYAGE: OR, An Eaſie way to guide a Young Man towards all ſorts of VIRTUES.</p>
            <p>With an hundred MAXIMES, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian and Moral.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>W. Crook,</hi> at the <hi>Green Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon</hi> without <hi>Temple-Bar,</hi> near <hi>Deve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reux</hi> Court, 1683.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:133315:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:133315:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:133315:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:133315:3"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFUL Sir <hi>Thomas Grantham,</hi> K<hi rend="sup">nt.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HAving accidentally met with a ſmall <hi>French Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual,</hi> newly printed in <hi>France;</hi> I found it fraught with ſuch <hi>excellent Advice</hi> and <hi>uncommon In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, not only</hi> for all Young Men in general, <hi>but more eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally</hi> for a Young Perſon upon his going <hi>a great Voyage by Sea,</hi> that I eſteem'd it well worthy (for the Benefit of <hi>our</hi> young
<pb facs="tcp:133315:4"/>Noblemen and Gentlemen eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Day vying who ſhall go firſt <hi>to Sea,</hi>) to be render'd into <hi>our Tongue;</hi> and that it may have the <hi>more Credit</hi> and <hi>Reputation</hi> with thoſe hopeful young Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men (or with any other that ſhall happen to peruſe it,) I have been bold, <hi>Sir,</hi> to offer it up to you, to be protected by <hi>your Name,</hi> under whoſe <hi>Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage</hi> and <hi>Protection</hi> my Father hath now put <hi>me,</hi> during your preſent Expedition <hi>to viſit</hi> all the conſiderable <hi>Ports</hi> and <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens</hi> in the <hi>East Indies;</hi> humbly begging you to take in good part this <hi>ſmall Token</hi> of my <hi>great Reſpect</hi> towards you, <hi>You</hi> who
<pb facs="tcp:133315:4"/>have deſerv'd the <hi>Reſpect</hi> of <hi>all Loyal Engliſh Men,</hi> and whom <hi>his Majesty</hi> hath <hi>ſo far</hi> reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as lately, <hi>Sir,</hi> to name you Commander of the <hi>best Merchant Ship</hi> that ever was built in <hi>England;</hi> and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the <hi>Honour</hi> of <hi>Knighthood</hi> upon you at the ſame time, as <hi>part</hi> of your Reward for the <hi>Signal Service</hi> you did <hi>his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty</hi> and <hi>this Nation,</hi> not only in the Year 1676 at <hi>Virginia,</hi> by reducing to <hi>their Allegiance</hi> that <hi>rebellious Colony,</hi> who had <hi>ravaged</hi> all the Country, <hi>burnt</hi> the City of <hi>James-Town,</hi> and <hi>driven away</hi> the Governour, whom you re-ſettled in his
<pb facs="tcp:133315:5"/>Government; for which <hi>his Majeſty (always bountiful</hi> to his faithful Servants) gratified you with a <hi>conſiderable Sum</hi> of <hi>Money;</hi> but alſo in 1678, for your <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable Valour,</hi> and admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Succeſs, againſt that po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Pirate <hi>Canary Admiral of Algier</hi> in the <hi>New Roſe,</hi> who attack'd your <hi>ſole Merchant Ship</hi> of but <hi>twenty two Guns,</hi> and <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Sea-men;</hi> with his <hi>Man</hi> of <hi>War</hi> of <hi>forty eight Guns,</hi> and <hi>ſix hundred Men;</hi> whom, after <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Hours Fight,</hi> you forced to ſtand away, with the <hi>loſs</hi> of <hi>two hundred Men,</hi> there being <hi>kill'd</hi> of <hi>yours</hi> not above <hi>ſeven</hi> or <hi>eight;</hi> for which Service
<pb facs="tcp:133315:5"/>
               <hi>his Majeſty</hi> was pleas'd to give you the <hi>best Medal</hi> and <hi>Chain</hi> that he ever yet beſtow'd upon any Man: ſo that <hi>his Majeſty</hi> accounts it a <hi>part</hi> of his Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs that he hath ſuch a <hi>Wiſe, Valiant,</hi> and <hi>Able Sea-man.</hi> And you cannot, <hi>Sir,</hi> but eſteem your ſelf exceedingly happy in the Favour and Service of <hi>ſuch a Prince,</hi> who knows better than any other <hi>Prince</hi> in <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> and conſequently in the <hi>World,</hi> how to value and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the Merits of all brave <hi>Sea Commanders</hi> and <hi>Officers;</hi> who knows better than <hi>all</hi> his <hi>Royal Predeceſſors,</hi> that the chief Intereſt of <hi>England</hi> is to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb facs="tcp:133315:6"/>the <hi>Empire</hi> and <hi>Soveraignty</hi> of the <hi>Britiſh Seas,</hi> and for that Reaſon, hath made it his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Buſineſs and Delight in <hi>Maritime Affairs,</hi> in <hi>Building, Rigging, Victualling,</hi> and <hi>Sailing</hi> of <hi>Ships;</hi> in underſtanding all our <hi>Ports, Harbours, Roads, Coasts, Seas, Flats, Sands,</hi> and above all, the <hi>best</hi> way of <hi>Naval Battels;</hi> in cheriſhing and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging all ingenious and expert Men for <hi>building</hi> of <hi>Ships,</hi> for <hi>casting</hi> the <hi>best Guns,</hi> for <hi>making</hi> the <hi>best Tackle,</hi> &amp;c. in favouring and encouraging all <hi>Young Noblemen</hi> and <hi>Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> who have any Deſire to ſerve their <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Country at
<pb facs="tcp:133315:6"/>Sea;</hi> in providing for the Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Youth in <hi>Navigation,</hi> and other <hi>Mathematical Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces;</hi> in taking Care for poor maim'd <hi>Sea Souldiers</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners;</hi> and laſtly, (to the great advantage of this Nation) in making choice of <hi>Captains</hi> for <hi>His Majeſties Ships,</hi> who for <hi>Wiſdom, Conduct, Courage,</hi> and other <hi>Abilities,</hi> excell all others in the World; ſuch as the Right Honourable Lord, the Baron of <hi>Dartmouth,</hi> the <hi>Vice-Admiral Herbert,</hi> Sir <hi>Richard Haddock,</hi> Sir <hi>John Norborough,</hi> Sir <hi>John Berry,</hi> Sir <hi>John Wet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wang,</hi> Sir <hi>John Wybourn,</hi> and many more <hi>ſtout, able, experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enc'd
<pb facs="tcp:133315:7"/>Commanders. Sir,</hi> it is but juſt that all the World ſhould be ſenſible of the Benefits and Advantages which his Majeſty hath brought with him into <hi>England,</hi> and that the <hi>Sea</hi> as well as the <hi>Land</hi> ſhould rejoyce thereat. This Kingdom was never <hi>ſo rich, ſo potent, ſo glorious,</hi> nor every way <hi>ſo flouriſhing,</hi> nor <hi>ſo happy</hi> (maugre all the <hi>wicked Deſigns</hi> and <hi>Helliſh Conſpiracies</hi> of thoſe <hi>ambitious, revengeful, muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Spirits</hi> amongſt us,) as in <hi>this Kings Reign,</hi> for above theſe twenty three Years; nor was there ever owing <hi>ſo much</hi> to any of our <hi>Princes</hi> as to <hi>this:</hi> the Conſideration whereof is, I
<pb facs="tcp:133315:7"/>believe, the <hi>chief Motive</hi> which induceth you to quit a <hi>Country quiet Life</hi> and <hi>plentiful Eſtate,</hi> and at <hi>his Majeſty's Deſire,</hi> to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take this long and long-laſting Voyage, which, <hi>Sir,</hi> I pray <hi>God</hi> to proſper, and encline you to continue your <hi>Favour</hi> to <hi>him</hi> who is both by <hi>Inclination</hi> and <hi>Obligation,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt Humble, moſt Devoted, and moſt Obedient Servant, <hi>Peregrin Clifford Chamberlayne.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:133315:8"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:133315:8"/>
            <head>Moral Inſtructions of a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to his Son, upon his departure for a long Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age.</head>
            <p>YOU earneſtly intreated me, <hi>my Son,</hi> to agree to your deſire of taking a Voyage into the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> and to be abſent for ſome Years. I did ſo little expect ſuch a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal from you, that it wholly ſurprized me, and I had ſeveral Reaſons perſuading me you could not be capable of making a Reſolution of this nature. So many things ought to concur thereto, that at firſt Thoughts I imagined, that either the Youthful and Ardent Deſires (inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent in thoſe of your Age) of travelling into Foreign Countries, had made you take up this Reſolution; or that it was perhaps only to try that Paternal Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:133315:9"/>which has ever been towards you moſt indulgent. Whatever it be, it is convenient that I put you in mind how I have acted all along in this Affair, and you ought to approve of my Proceedings. You know that while I endeavoured to diſſuade you from this Deſign, I did not onely make you recall to mind all thoſe ſweet and pleaſant hours you have ſpent hitherto under the Roof of a loving Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and rendred you ſenſible of the <hi>Cares</hi> and <hi>Toils</hi> you were to undergo during your whole Voyage, inſtead of that <hi>Tranquility</hi> which lay in your pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to enjoy: But I alſo demonſtrated to you, how many ſeveral Reaſons did ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige you not to abandon me; yet ſeeing you eſteemed theſe Reaſons of too little force to make you change your Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, I oppos'd it by the conſideration of the great <hi>Hazards</hi> in your <hi>Paſſage:</hi> In order thereunto I laid before you the danger of <hi>Shipwrack, Pirats,</hi> and <hi>Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies</hi> both infinite and unavoidable in ſuch a long Voyage, principally to a Young Man bred ſo tenderly, and edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated with that Care as you have bin. All this was not ſufficient to diſſuade
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:133315:9"/>you, ſo that I was forced at length to yield to your requeſt, whereto the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance you gave me did not a little con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute, that the impatience of becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more worthy of my ſingular Care in your Education, did prompt you to this, beſides your mentioning what Joy you ſhould conceive to ſhare the Pains I take to increaſe your Fortune. The Proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of this truth made to me in private, and reiterated in the preſence of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, who I was willing ſhould be wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of my Carriage towards you in an Affair of this importance, prevented my making uſe of an abſolute Authority, (given to me as a Father) to force you to comply with my Will; and that for three Reaſons, which I ſhall the more gladly impart to you, becauſe I am preſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the knowledg of them will excite you to acknowledge my Kindneſs.</p>
            <p>The firſt is, That altho many Fathers will admit of no Limits in Filial Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and their claim thereto being of Divine Right, yet I can ſay I never took ſuch advantage over you by this Right, as to uſe it in it's utmoſt Rigour: Of this I have given you more than one
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:133315:10"/>Proof, and you may remember, that as often as your Conduct brought upon you my Correction, in the greateſt and moſt lawful Cauſes I had of being incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, I always allayed the heat of thoſe Provocations, cauſed through your In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcretion, with the Fondneſs of a tender Father. You know I have <hi>Contracted</hi> the <hi>Bounds</hi> of your obedience, and <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended thoſe</hi> of my Kindneſs to whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver you could pretend; and in putting you in mind of your <hi>Duty,</hi> by theſe words of St. <hi>Paul; Children, obey your Parents in all things, for this is well-pleaſing unto the Lord;</hi> I was exhorted to mine, by the words following: <hi>Fathers, provoke not your Children to Anger, leaſt they be diſcouraged.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſecond Reaſon,</hi> which obliged me not to withſtand abſolutely your Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, was to avoid the Reproaches which you might reflect upon me hereafter, that my refuſal had bin an Obſtacle to your Fortune.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And the laſt</hi> was, the Fear I had leſt you ſhould have made uſe of that very refuſal for a Pretext to juſtifie ever after all defects in your Proceedings.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:133315:10"/>
            <p>Theſe Reaſons, <hi>my Son,</hi> were the Cauſe of my complying ſo eaſily with your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt. I could have wiſhed you would have altered your Intentions, to pleaſe me; but ſeeing that you could not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form to my Sentiments, and that you ſtill perſiſt in your deſign, after having implored the <hi>Almighty</hi> to grant you his Grace, and to Shower down the moſt precious of his Bleſſings upon your <hi>Soul,</hi> your <hi>Perſon,</hi> and your <hi>Actions,</hi> I think it is abſolutely neceſſary, (for to ſatisfie my Inclination and Duty) not to let you go without ſome peculiar Inſtructions, which may be as a Guide to your Manners, and which moſt certainly will be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing Proofs of my Kindneſs, as alſo inexhauſtible Springs of future happineſs, in your Converſation both Spiritual and Civil, if you will apply your ſelf to them, which I exhort and command you to do. However let what will happen, theſe Inſtructions will remain as ſo many irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fragable Witneſſes, how zealouſly I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to do <hi>my Duty,</hi> if unhapily you ſhould be wanting <hi>in yours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By telling you, <hi>my dear Son,</hi> that theſe Inſtructions which I am about to give
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:133315:11"/>you, are the Effects of my <hi>Inclination</hi> and <hi>Duty,</hi> I have inverted that order which Reaſon requires: I ſhould rather have ſaid, theſe Effects proceeded from my <hi>Duty</hi> and <hi>Inclination,</hi> and ſo have preferred <hi>Duty before Inclination,</hi> becauſe the <hi>firſt</hi> is governed by <hi>Reaſon,</hi> whereas the <hi>latter</hi> is but an <hi>Incitement</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> who is not ſeldom blinded by thoſe ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Impulſes which Proximity of Blood inſpires. But I was overcome by a Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, common to moſt Fathers, which I do not ſtick to confeſs, to the intent you may be perſwaded, that in this following Diſcourſe I rather fell into a great Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, than that I maintained a Severity too Auſtere.</p>
            <p>'Tis alſo not without ſome Myſtery, <hi>my Son,</hi> that in wiſhing you the <hi>Bleſſings</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> I would have them applied to your <hi>Soul,</hi> your <hi>Perſon,</hi> and your <hi>Actions.</hi> The order of theſe Words is one of the Duties whereon I ſhall give you ſome In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, which I enjoyn you to obſerve and practice. I divide it into three parts, <hi>Spiritual, Perſonal,</hi> and <hi>Civil Duties:</hi> the firſt ſhall teach you your <hi>Duty to God;</hi> the ſecond, your <hi>Duty to your ſelf;</hi> and the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:133315:11"/>laſt ſhall inſtruct you in your <hi>Duty to your Neighbour.</hi> If I ſhould go about to treat of this Matter to an extent as great as it's Importance, I ought, inſtead of a few Pages I intend for you, to write ſeveral Volumes: but this being wide of my Deſign, as alſo far above my Abilities, I ſhall reſt ſatisfied in being as conciſe as this matter can poſſibly allow. God grant through his Grace, that I may be inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with Arguments, both ſo clear and ſtrong, as to equalize the greatneſs of my Enterprize; and that through his Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, he may encline you to put them in Practice for his Glory, for your Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for my Satisfaction, and for your Profit and Advancement.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Spiritual Duties.</head>
               <p>YOU learned in your Childhood, <hi>my Son,</hi> that <hi>God</hi> created you to <hi>know</hi> him, and to <hi>ſerve</hi> him. Theſe two Obligations which bind you from your Birth, have Relation to the two chief <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties</hi> of the <hi>Soul.</hi> The <hi>Knowledge</hi> of <hi>God</hi> belongs to the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> and the <hi>Service</hi> of him to the <hi>Will;</hi> but the Light
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:133315:12"/>of our Underſtanding has too narrow li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits ever to arrive to the perfect Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of his Divinity, and the Will of Man is too perverſe to be capable of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him as we ought. Theſe Impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which grow out of the abundance of our Corruption, muſt nevertheleſs not diſcourage us; <hi>A bruiſed Reed God ſhall not break, and ſmoaking Flax ſhall he not quench:</hi> He fulfils his Power in our Weakneſſes; he ſupplies our Wants; he helps our Infirmities; and he, knowing that of our ſelves we cannot aſcend to him, out of his Divine Goodneſs is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to come down to us. He not only makes uſe of his Word and his Works to imprint in our Minds ſome kind of <hi>Idea</hi> of his Greatneſs, which we may not wholly conceive; but alſo, through the Communication of his Holy Spirit he corrects our Inclinations; and when he has made them <hi>to will</hi> what naturally they <hi>would not,</hi> he alſo forces them <hi>to act</hi> it by a ſweet ſort of Violence which we cannot reſiſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>My Son,</hi> read this Word, and that as often as poſſibly you may; but read it with great <hi>Reſpect</hi> and <hi>Attention:</hi> 'Tis the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:133315:12"/>Voice of <hi>God:</hi> This Reaſon muſt oblige you to the <hi>Respect;</hi> and 'tis for your In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction you read it: this ſhould force you to the <hi>Attention</hi> I demand of you. Set apart ſome hours for this ſacred Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, which on <hi>Sunday</hi> ought to be two at leaſt, and one upon each <hi>other Day.</hi> Be careful that upon no account you ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect this Duty. The greateſt of all Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations is that of your Salvation: quit all others that you may not fail in this; and let not any intereſt or pleaſure here upon Earth make you forget thoſe Joys of Heaven. The World, and all worldly Deſires paſs away, but he whoſe Deſire is the Will of <hi>God</hi> ſhall live eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally. This Will you may learn in his holy Word. Yet what will ſignifie the Knowledge of it, but to render your ſelf more guilty, unleſs you uſe your utmoſt Endeavours to be conformable thereto? That Servant <hi>who knoweth</hi> the <hi>Will</hi> of his <hi>Maſter,</hi> and <hi>doth it not,</hi> ſhall be beaten with more Stripes than he who never knew it. Remember this with Fear and Trembling. However, all your Care would be in vain if God himſelf did not help you to bring to paſs what he requires;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:133315:13"/>therefore always beg that Grace of him. 'Tis a very great benefit that he permits us to ſpeak to him; yet it is a benefit much greater, that not only he vouchſafes to let us ſpeak to him in our Prayers, but alſo promiſeth through his Mercy to hear us; <hi>Call upon me,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>in the Day of Trouble, and I will deliver thee.</hi> Implore him then, <hi>my Son,</hi> but let your Prayers aſcend upon the Wings of Faith and Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vency; for God can no more love thoſe who want Zeal, than thoſe that miſtruſt his Goodneſs. Ask earneſtly of him that he accompliſh in you, by his Vertue om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent, whatſoever he commands; and be not weary of performing ſo holy an Exerciſe. Beſeech him earneſtly to direct your ways, that you may follow after him. Implore him inceſſantly, that he would raiſe you from that Sepulchre of Sins wherein you lye buried. Theſe are they, who by their Prayers ſtorm the Kingdom of Heaven, and take it by force. Follow the Example of <hi>Jacob,</hi> who by a <hi>holy Importunity</hi> gained a Bleſſing from <hi>God.</hi> Without ſuch a Bleſſing, all your Labour, Care, and Diligence, will be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in vain. <hi>Except the Lord build the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:133315:13"/>Houſe they labour in vain that build it. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin</hi> and <hi>end</hi> the Day with <hi>Prayer,</hi> and be conſtant in your Morning and Evening Sacrifice. If you hope to obtain what you ask of <hi>God,</hi> let your Heart pray rather than your Lips; with a devout Zeal, and not for Faſhion-ſake. Begin your <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> with Joy and Gladneſs, go through with them cheerfully, and do not end them without a ſorrowful Reluctancy that you muſt leave off. But above all, let this <hi>Beginning,</hi> this <hi>Continuance,</hi> and this <hi>End,</hi> be without any wandering of your Mind. Frighten away thoſe Birds which come to trouble your Sacrifice; that is, put far from you thoſe Thoughts which may be the leaſt hinderance to your De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion. To pray to God without Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, inſtead of pleaſing doth offend him; it is a Sacriledge rather than an Offering. Our being ſeldom diſpoſed for heavenly things renders this Attention difficult. Yet it is moſt certain, that from <hi>thence</hi> we have moſt reaſon to derive the Succeſs of our Prayers; for <hi>God</hi> cannot grant our Requeſts unleſs he hear us, and how ſhould we expect to have <hi>thoſe Prayers</hi> heard which we our ſelves do not hear?
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:133315:14"/>Upon this very Account, <hi>God</hi> may apply to us what he ſaid in time paſt to the <hi>Jews; This People draw near me with their Mouth, and with their Lips do honour me, but have removed their Hearts far from me.</hi> Judge therefore, <hi>my Son,</hi> if we have not great reaſon to ſearch diligently after the <hi>Means</hi> which will bring us to this Attention.</p>
               <p>I have here ſet down ſome few Rules or Means, the Practice whereof I take to be very advantageous, and conſequently not to be neglected.</p>
               <p>We may pray to <hi>God</hi> in <hi>all Places,</hi> but all Places are not equally proper for this Duty. When thou prayeſt, ſaith our <hi>Saviour, enter into thy Cloſet, and when thou haſt ſhut thy Door, pray to thy Father which is in ſecret.</hi> This Advice which the Saviour of the World gives concerning Prayer, teacheth us that we muſt retire our ſelves when we Pray, and muſt be ſo far from making our Prayers the Subject of <hi>Humane Applauſe,</hi> that we muſt <hi>pray ſecretly;</hi> which not only our Divine Maſter did confirm by his own Example, but alſo before he gave his Apoſtles that Counſel of withdrawing in private, he told them: <hi>When ye pray, be not as the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:133315:14"/>Hypocrites are: For they love to pray ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the</hi> Synagogues, <hi>and in the corners of the Streets, that they may be ſeen of Men.</hi> Obſerve theſe Maxims, and when you would offer up your Prayers, let it be <hi>in Private;</hi> for going to an Exerciſe which obligeth you to fly the World, let not any thing that is worldly accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany you at that time. Do not imitate the Example of <hi>Rachel,</hi> who leaving her Fathers Houſe carried with her thoſe Images, which were the Object of his Idolatry. Follow rather that of <hi>Elijah,</hi> who, when he drew near to <hi>God,</hi> in the Chariot wherein he was carried from this World, let fall his Mantle, that he might have no Earthly thing with him. <hi>Draw not nigh hither. Put off thy Shooes from off thy Feet, for the place whereon thou ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt is holy Ground,</hi> ſaid the <hi>Eternal</hi> to <hi>Moſes,</hi> when he ſpake to him out of the burning Buſh. This Voice is alſo direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to you. When at any time you have a mind to pray, the place you chooſe out for that purpoſe you muſt ſuppoſe to be ſanctified with the preſence of <hi>God.</hi> Put off then your Shooes, that it may not be defiled; that is, relinquiſh all your
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:133315:15"/>Thoughts which ſavour of the World or the Fleſh. Depart from <hi>Sodom,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out looking behind you; and having diſpoſed things in this order, fall down upon your Knees before you begin your Devotion, ſpare ſome ſmall time to think upon the infinite Greatneſs of him you are about to implore, and to conſider your own extream Meanneſs. If <hi>ſuch a Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as this</hi> is ſerious, it muſt of Neceſſity redouble your Zeal, and render you more fit to approach the Divine Majeſty. One great Reaſon why our Mind is too often alienated at Prayer is, the Diverſity of Objects which our Eyes meet with, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to prevent this great inconvenience, I think it Neceſſary to keep them ſhut. This Advice, <hi>my Son,</hi> is not of the leaſt Moment, fail not to try it, and then make uſe of it according as you find it ſucceed.</p>
               <p>I do not preſcribe you the uſe of any particular Prayers; your Diſcretion ought to make choice of ſuch as are ſuitable to the Subject which <hi>occaſions</hi> your Prayers. However I think it will not be amiſs, that all the Requeſts you make to <hi>God</hi> be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed in this one, <hi>that of his Love.</hi> This is the way to have all; for he who has
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:133315:15"/>
                  <hi>God</hi> with him can want nothing. <hi>Solomon</hi> asked of him only Wiſdom, and <hi>God</hi> ſaid to him, <hi>Becauſe that thou haſt asked this thing, and that thou haſt not asked for thy ſelf long Life; neither haſt asked Riches; nor the Life of thine Enemies; but haſt asked for thy ſelf <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding: It ſhall be given thee; and I will give thee that which thou haſt not asked, both Riches and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. Plato,</hi> although a <hi>Pagan,</hi> may be an <hi>Example</hi> to many Chriſtians to teach them for what things they ought to pray. It was his cuſtom in <hi>his Prayers</hi> to ſay thus: <hi>O God grant me thoſe things that are good, when I ask them not, and deny me, when I ask for thoſe things that are evil. God</hi> often favours us by not hearing our Prayers, and ſometimes puniſheth us by granting our requeſts, when we pray for that which is pernicious to our welfare; as we common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly do, for as our Lord JESUS CHRIST ſaid, we often know not what we ask.</p>
               <p>Phyſicians order thoſe who have a weak Stomach, to eat little and often. If it be hard for you to keep up your Attention, (which is the Soul of Prayer,) do you after the ſame manner, and following the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of our <hi>Bleſſed Saviour,</hi> when you pray,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:133315:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>uſe not vain repetitions as the Heathen do; for they think they ſhall be heard for their much ſpeaking.</hi> If therefore your Prayers muſt be ſhort, let them be the more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, but chiefly, I ſhall once again ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort you to this; Let neither your Zeal nor your Faith be wanting.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>My Son,</hi> if you remember, I ſaid we might pray to <hi>God</hi> in <hi>all Places,</hi> though all places were not equally <hi>Proper</hi> for this Exerciſe; Yet if we conſider Prayer to be (as we muſt not doubt) a darting forth of our Soul towards <hi>God,</hi> to unite it with his Holy Spirit; why cannot we do this <hi>every Hour,</hi> if not <hi>every Moment</hi> in the Day, whereſoever we are, at home or abroad? And why cannot we often turn our Hearts to <hi>God,</hi> though in the midſt of our moſt important Affairs, and in walking, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be in the City, or in the Country? To do thus, is to pray to him. The Heart of Man is a <hi>moving Cloſet,</hi> a Place of Retirement; a holy Solitude, where we may enter every Moment, and from thence ſend ſuch fervent (though ſhort) Ejaculations as ſhall penetrate Heaven, and be more acceptable to <hi>God,</hi> than thoſe long Prayers which too often want At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:133315:16"/>Theſe Ejaculations are without doubt what the Evangeliſt means, when he exhorts us to <hi>pray always.</hi> And why, <hi>my Son,</hi> ſhould you not obſerve this good Cuſtom, of praying to <hi>God,</hi> and praiſing him <hi>in your Bed,</hi> whenſoever you happen to awake, ſince Prayer is ſo much the <hi>principal part</hi> of Divine Worſhip, that the Scripture comprehends thereby all Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Duties.</p>
               <p>This, <hi>my Son,</hi> is the chiefeſt of what I had to ſay to you concerning Prayer in particular: But take notice you cannot pray to <hi>God</hi> without putting your Truſt in him, neither can you put your truſt in <hi>God</hi> without loving him. Love him then if you expect his Love. Fear him if you deſire to be wiſe; for <hi>the Fear of the Lord is the beginning of Wiſdom.</hi> This fear, as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaid, is to hate and avoid all evil, and conſequently to do good. If you fear <hi>God,</hi> you will love him, and if you love him, you will keep his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements: <hi>my Son,</hi> you know all thoſe Commandements; let nothing then be an Obſtacle to your Practice of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>God</hi> is a Spirit, and the Truth, and he will be worſhipped in Spirit and Truth. This
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:133315:17"/>Religion, wherein (through his goodneſs) you was born, for the full and perfect Knowledge whereof, I have throughly cultivated your Underſtanding; This, I ſay, is the only natural Worſhip which he requires. Adhere to this Worſhip, and you will find it more advantageous to you, than the Star was to thoſe Shepherds whom it guided to <hi>Bethlehem;</hi> for that only led them to JESUS CHRIST in his loweſt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, whereas this Worſhip ſhall conduct you to him in his Glory. This Divine <hi>Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our</hi> of the World, ſpeaking of himſelf to St. <hi>Thomas,</hi> ſaid, <hi>I am the Way, the Truth, and the Life.</hi> And 'tis the only way through which we muſt go to the Father. Stray not from it, <hi>my Son,</hi> whatſoever may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall you: For inſtead of Springs which you will find in this Way, flowing with living Water, every where out of it you ſhall meet with puddles of Water both impure and loathſome. You cannot go out of this Path wherein you have entred with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out departing from <hi>God,</hi> and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from all thoſe Joys whereof he is the Center. Let neither <hi>Wealth, Honour,</hi> nor <hi>Pleaſure</hi> lead you aſide; and though you ſuffer the moſt rigorous Perſecutions, yet
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:133315:17"/>be not diſheartned. Eſteem it as a great Honour to bear the Croſs after your <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour;</hi> it would be an honourable Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to you, to have your Body mark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and bruiſed for the ſake of Chriſt. This is the way, through which all the Martyrs have paſſed, to enter into thoſe heavenly Joys. If <hi>God</hi> ſhould call you to ſuch Proofs, turn not away, for the <hi>leaſt Thron</hi> falling from our <hi>Saviour</hi>'s Crown upon your Head, will affix thereto a <hi>Crown of Glory:</hi> If therefore you happen to ſuffer for <hi>Chriſts</hi> ſake, be not aſhamed, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther praiſe and glorifie <hi>God</hi> for it.</p>
               <p>Sickneſs, Loſs of Perſons dear to us, Loſs of Goods, Wealth, and an infinite number more of unwelcome Accidents, compoſe generally the <hi>Series</hi> of our Life. <hi>My Son,</hi> do not think you can avoid them. The Afflictions of this World are moſt certain Characters of the <hi>Children</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> wherewith he corrects thoſe he loves, as a Father uſeth a rod to chaſtiſe the Child whom he tenderly cheriſheth. 'Tis true the Fleſh takes no delight in being chaſtiſed, neither are we to hearken to <hi>Fleſhly Sentiments</hi> when we would put in practice what is neceſſary to our Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:133315:18"/>If it is <hi>God</hi>'s good Pleaſure you ſhould undergo Afflictions, of what nature, or how ſharp ſoever, murmur not. Take heed when you ſuffer, it be <hi>not deſerved<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly:</hi> And remember in your ſufferings, though exceeding great, that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be equal to the Glory, which will be your reward hereafter. Theſe afflictions (which if the right uſe be made of them immediately paſs away) will produce in your Mind the Brightneſs of that tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendent Glory. Moral Philoſophy teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us, that Vices of all ſorts ſpring from Paſſions diſorder'd, whereas from regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated Paſſions do proceed all Vertues; And Chriſtian Divinity doth verifie by experience, that afflictions, which in Reprobates occaſion nothing but Deſpair, are to the Faithful ſo many inexhauſtible Fountains of Joy.</p>
               <p>The Rods which <hi>God</hi> makes uſe of to puniſh the Wicked, are like that of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> which turned into a <hi>Serpent;</hi> and thoſe wherewith he chaſtiſeth his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, have a reſemblance to that of <hi>Aaron,</hi> which brought forth <hi>Flowers</hi> and <hi>Fruit.</hi> Make good uſe of them, <hi>My Son;</hi> Kiſs thoſe Rods wherewith he corrects you;
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:133315:18"/>adore the ſecret Vertue in them, and, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in the moſt Severe Chaſtiſements, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge his Divine Goodneſs in rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing you out of that heavy Sleep wherein Sin may have caſt you. If they are more ſharp than Fleſh could wiſh for, believe that it is for your good to be thus afflicted for a little time, <hi>that the trial of your Faith being much more precious than of Gold that periſheth, tho it be tried with Fire, might be found unto Praiſe, and Honour, and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, at the appearing of</hi> JESUS CHRIST.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>My Son,</hi> you ought to have obſerved, that I have reduced under <hi>four Heads</hi> all the Duties of a Spiritual Life; <hi>viz: Reading the Word of God with Attention; frequent and ardent Prayers; a conſtant Perſeverence in the Faith;</hi> and <hi>a perfect and entire Reſignation to the Will of God,</hi> tho he expoſe you to be tried by the moſt bitter Calamities. If you had ſtill remained with me, I ſhould have given you theſe very Inſtructions, the <hi>two firſt</hi> whereof I have bin very careful in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king you practice as ſoon as your Age would permit it: Therefore I could not but think them more neceſſary to you when you are from me, and chiefly in
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:133315:19"/>a Country, where, far from having the Comfort of a publick Exerciſe of your Religion, you will ſcarce ever ſee an Example of the leaſt Piety; which ought the rather to oblige you to practiſe moſt exactly the Advice I have now given you. <hi>I do exhort you to</hi> it by the Bowels of Mercy of our <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Saviour; I require</hi> it of you by the Care you ought to have of your Salvation; and <hi>I do en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat</hi> you to do it by that Complaiſance which I have reaſon to expect from your Gratitude. If you follow this Counſel, you will render to <hi>God</hi> what is due to him, you will accompliſh the demands of your <hi>Father;</hi> and thereby you may diſcharge that Duty you owe to <hi>your ſelf;</hi> wherein I ſhall inſtruct you in the ſecond Diſcourſe, which, according to the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod I preſcribed, muſt treat of <hi>Perſonal Duties.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Perſonal Duties.</head>
               <p>I Have been more conciſe in the firſt Part, which treats of your <hi>Duty to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God,</hi> than I ſhall be in this, which concerns your <hi>Duty to your ſelf,</hi> or in the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:133315:19"/>next following, which comprehends your <hi>Duty to your Neighbour:</hi> and 'tis no hard matter to juſtifie my Proceedings in this Point: I have followed the Example of <hi>God</hi> himſelf; for, of the <hi>Ten Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> whereof his Law is compoſed, there are but <hi>four</hi> which have immediate Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to <hi>his Service,</hi> whereas there are <hi>ſix</hi> to guide us in our <hi>Duty towards our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.</hi> There is no Nation ſo ignorant or brutiſh but believeth in ſome <hi>God,</hi> and at the ſame time prepares a form of Worſhip whereby to ſhew their Obedience; ſo true it is that the Belief of a God doth imply a Duty of ſerving him not to be diſpenſed with: and this is ſo abſolutely neceſſary, that altho ſome Men might be ſo irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious as not to acknowledge it, they muſt nevertheleſs be convinced of it in their Conſcience. Your Mind, <hi>my Son,</hi> is repleniſhed with this Knowledge, let it then paſs from thence into your Will; and with <hi>thoſe Lights,</hi> wherewith it hath pleaſed <hi>God</hi> to enlighten your Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, rectifie whatſoever is amiſs in your Affections. Diſcharge your ſelf of the Duties that are inſeparably joyned to your Knowledge of <hi>God;</hi> that is, to fear,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:133315:20"/>to <hi>love,</hi> and to <hi>ſerve him.</hi> I do not que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion but you would have done this tho I had not exhorted you to it; which will be a matter of great Comfort in my Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for your Abſence. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon this Belief</hi> I abridg'd my Thoughts, and ſuppreſſed much of what I could have ſaid upon this Subject, which being ſo abundant, would have render'd this Diſcourſe at leaſt as long as both thoſe which are to follow.</p>
               <p>To being with our ſecond Subject, which is, concerning your <hi>Duty to your ſelf,</hi> I think it very convenient to put you in mind of that moral Dialogue which in your tender Years I made for your Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions; wherein you may have remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber'd that I treated of <hi>Chriſtian Vertues,</hi> which are, <hi>Faith, Charity,</hi> and <hi>Hope;</hi> which three, guide us in our <hi>Duty to God: Faith</hi> makes us ſubmit to him in <hi>all Things, Charity</hi> makes us cleave to him at <hi>all Times,</hi> and <hi>Hope</hi> carrieth us to him to <hi>all Eternity.</hi> You ought alſo to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that there are <hi>Moral Vertues; viz: Prudence, Fortiude, Temperance,</hi> and <hi>Justice:</hi> Theſe are to teach us our <hi>Duty to our ſelves,</hi> as alſo our Duty <hi>to our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours.</hi> The firſt of theſe four Vertues is
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:133315:20"/>like a Salt to ſeaſon the other three: <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude</hi> and <hi>Temperance</hi> have a relation to each individual Perſon; and <hi>Juſtice</hi> is the Bonds of Humane Society, without which Men muſt live together like Wolves, not being capable of any Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe for the Publick Good, which, next to the glorifying of <hi>God,</hi> ought to be our chief Aim: So that in this ſecond Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of Inſtructions which, <hi>my Son,</hi> I do now lay down before you, I muſt ſpeak but of the three firſt Vertues; <hi>Prudence, Temperance,</hi> and <hi>Fortitude. Prudence</hi> ought to be the Rule of your <hi>Actions</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct. Temperance</hi> will inſtruct you how to govern your ſelf in <hi>Proſperity,</hi> that you may not be poiſoned with it's delicious Pleaſures: And <hi>Fortitude</hi> will ſo guide you, that you ſhall not be overcome with the Bitterneſs of <hi>Adverſity.</hi> I will reduce all I have to ſay to you to as few words as I can (altho the Subject be very copious) that you may only receive the Pith and Juyce of it, whereby you may be nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed without being overcharged.</p>
               <p>Man was born for Society, and I may ſay, without that Society Vertue would
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:133315:21"/>have no Followers, Man's Life would be unpleaſant, and in this World there would be no Content. <hi>God,</hi> after he had created Man, ſaid <hi>it was not good that he ſhould be alone:</hi> Therefore through his extraordinary Goodneſs, <hi>he made him a Help meet for him,</hi> and formed a Perſon with whom he might live in Society. Now this Society is nothing elſe but a reciprocal Communication made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween divers Perſons, who by mutual Services to one another endeavour to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their Lives as pleaſant as they can, and to avoid vexatious Cares and Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row. According to the Humor of the Perſons which make up this Society, it will be good or evil; for, as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>He that walketh with wiſe men ſhall be wiſe; but a Companion of Fools ſhall be deſtroyed.</hi> Evil Communication corrupts good Manners; therefore, <hi>my Son,</hi> you ought diligently to take heed in the choice of thoſe Perſons with whom you deſign to be acquainted. Hearken not to <hi>Nature</hi> herein, who (following her In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination to what is evil) might lead you into bad Company; be rather attentive to <hi>true Piety,</hi> which will tell you, <hi>Enter
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:133315:21"/>not into the Path of the Wicked, and go not in the way of evil Men.</hi> Conſult Prudence, and ſhe will teach you to chooſe your Friends, which is a thing of the higheſt conſequence; becauſe we acquire gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally the <hi>Habits</hi> and <hi>Paſſions</hi> of thoſe whom we frequent: This was ſo well known to our Fore-fathers, that they did not ſcruple to paſs their Judgment upon any Man when they were once acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Temper of his Companions; according to this old Saying of theirs, <hi>Tell me what Company you keep and I will tell you what you are.</hi> Frequent then, <hi>my Son,</hi> as much as you are able, Perſons of Honour and Integrity, or at leaſt thoſe who are <hi>eſteemed</hi> ſuch; and out of this Company chooſe one of the moſt vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous whom you muſt endeavour to make your particular Friend. Let not this ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle Expreſſion of <hi>one Friend</hi> ſurpriſe you, for it is not an eaſie matter to obtain ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>true Friends;</hi> nay, I take a <hi>true Friend</hi> to be a thing almoſt as rare in Humane Society, as the Philoſophers Stone is in Chymiſtry. Several People have made it their buſineſs all their Life-time to find a <hi>true Friend,</hi> and yet at laſt have miſſed
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:133315:22"/>their Aim. Uſe your utmoſt Endeavours to procure one; you will be happy if you can bring it to paſs: Do not ſpare Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaiſance, Reſpect, or any Service, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided you do not deſcend to what is low and infamous; which cannot be, if you chooſe a vertuous Perſon, as I have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed you, to bind your ſelf with, in a tender, ſincere, and ſtrict Friendſhip. Kindneſs muſt be repayed with Kindneſs: If you would be beloved, love. It is moſt certain, that a Correſpondence of Humours contributs extremely to our being beloved; therefore if you <hi>deſire</hi> the Friendſhip of a Man of Honour and Vertue, <hi>imitate</hi> his Vertue and that will facilitate your Deſire. When you have acquired this Friendſhip, be careful to avoid whatſoever may occaſion the loſs of it. Be before hand with him if you can, in Services, and in kind Reſpects towards him: If you have convincing Proofs that he hath given you his Heart, and if you have likewiſe yielded yours up to him, with-hold not your Purſe from him in his Neceſſity. If unhappily your Friendſhip upon any occaſion ſhould wax cold, and that out of Prudence you
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:133315:22"/>muſt part with him, let it not be a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Rupture, but retire by degrees. There is ſcarce any thing ſo juſt and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent an Obſtacle to the procuring or preſerving of Friendſhip, as <hi>Pride:</hi> This Sin was the cauſe that the <hi>firſt Angels</hi> were transferred from Heaven to Hell, and became the <hi>first Devils.</hi> Take great care not to be tainted with it; and if you ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect the Love of thoſe with whom you keep Company, be humble towards all. <hi>When Pride cometh then cometh Shame: but with the Lowly is Wiſdom,</hi> ſaith the Wiſe Man: <hi>God ſcorneth the Scorners; but he giveth Grace unto the Lowly. Every one that is proud in Heart is an Abomination to the Lord.</hi> The <hi>Proud</hi> have this misfortune to diſpleaſe every Body but themſelves. 'Tis impoſſible that a vain Man ſhould love to be blamed, and 'tis almoſt as impoſſible for a Man to be a Reaſonable Creature while he hateth Reproof. <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> aſſures us of it, in ſaying, <hi>Whoſo lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth Inſtruction loveth Knowledge: but he that hateth Reproof is brutiſh. Poverty and Shame ſhall be to him that refuſeth Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; but he that regardeth Reproof ſhall be honoured.</hi> If you deſire to be reſpected
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:133315:23"/>make your ſelf worthy of Reſpect; this muſt be done not only by ſhunning <hi>Pride;</hi> avoid alſo <hi>Covetouſneſs, Gluttony, Sloth, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs, Anger,</hi> and <hi>Envy;</hi> theſe are the Vices againſt which all the World cries out, and which nevertheleſs reign in all Parts of the World. In the ſame Order as they are mentioned I will lay down their reſpective Reaſons which ſhould provoke your Hatred of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Covetouſneſs</hi> is the Root of all Evil, and as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid to <hi>Timothy,</hi> it cauſeth Men to <hi>err from the Faith.</hi> It makes them fall into Temptation, into the Snares of the Devil, and into ſeveral inordinate and unſatiable Deſires, which at length plunge them into the Abyſs of Damnation. Our bleſſed Apoſtle did not reſt ſatisfied with this dreadful Deſcription, but in his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the <hi>Coloſſians</hi> calleth it Idolatry; becauſe it cannot poſſeſs any Heart with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out firſt expelling from thence all <hi>Fear</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and ſetting up in the Room the <hi>Love</hi> of the <hi>World</hi> and of <hi>Riches. Take heed, and beware of Covetouſneſs,</hi> ſaid our <hi>Saviour Christ,</hi> in St. <hi>Luke; for a Man's Life conſiſteth not in the abundance of the things which he poſſeſſeth. Covetouſneſs</hi>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:133315:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>takes all opportunities to heap up Riches; and tho the means are moſt unlawful, yet to her they always ſeem commendable enough: I ſay, her Deſign is to lay up Riches; for the <hi>covetous</hi> Man takes good heed not to make any <hi>uſe</hi> of them. He lives all his Life-time <hi>Poor,</hi> to have the Satisfaction of dying <hi>Rich;</hi> and inſtead of making them a <hi>Cauſe</hi> of his <hi>Salvation,</hi> through his prudent management of them and Contribution, they become through an ill uſe the <hi>Occaſion</hi> of his <hi>Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Before I proceed to ſpeak of the other Vices, (whoſe Deformities I purpoſe to diſcover to you to ſtir up your diſlike of them) I muſt put you in mind, that how great ſoever is Mans Inclination to Evil, yet he endeavours to hide that Vice to which he is inclined, under the Mask of ſome Vertue that has a reſemblance with it. This Example ſhall ſerve for all the reſt. The <hi>Covetous,</hi> tho he be deeply en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in that ſordid Paſſion, cannot but acknowledge the Vileneſs of it, yet in himſelf he makes it paſs for an <hi>honest Thriftineſs;</hi> this he firſt perſuades <hi>himſelf</hi> to believe, and then <hi>his Neighbours.</hi> All
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:133315:24"/>that are much tainted with any Vice, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the ſame Rule for their Juſtification: Of this, <hi>my Son,</hi> I have given you no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, that you may avoid the falling in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſo unreaſonable a Conduct; and that ſo you may not be reduced to cover a <hi>vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Inclination</hi> with the Veil of what is <hi>tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Vertuous.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After having given you this Advice, (which I thought expedient to be done) I ſhall ſpeak of <hi>Gluttony,</hi> as it follows next in courſe after <hi>Covetouſneſs.</hi> Theſe two in their <hi>Means</hi> are ſomething contrary, but their <hi>Effects</hi> do reſemble much. The <hi>Covetous</hi> picks up all things to increaſe <hi>Riches</hi> that are pernicious to him; and the <hi>Glutton</hi> lets all fly to procure thoſe <hi>Pleaſures</hi> which muſt be prejudicial to his Happineſs. The firſt, to content his <hi>raking Deſire,</hi> will abſtain from what is <hi>neceſſary;</hi> and the other, to ſatisfie his <hi>Senſual Appetite,</hi> will not abſtain from what is <hi>ſuperfluous.</hi> One <hi>locks up</hi> his Reaſon in his Cheſt with his Gold and Silver; and t'other <hi>drowns</hi> it in Wine and Dainties. What can be hoped from ſuch a Man? <hi>God</hi> ordained us to eat that we might live, and the <hi>Glutton</hi> ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:133315:24"/>that he lives only to eat; whereof he is ſo fully perſuaded, that it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for him to apply himſelf with plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to any Duty which is requiſite in a civil Society; nay, how can he do it with Pleaſure, he that knoweth no other Pleaſure than that of the <hi>Taſte,</hi> whoſe <hi>Kitchen</hi> is his <hi>Church,</hi> and who of his <hi>Belly</hi> makes his <hi>God.</hi> Avoid then this Sin, whoſe Effects are ſo pernicious; and in following my Counſel you will obey the Command of the Holy Scripture, <hi>viz. Be not amongſt Wine-bibbers, amongſt rio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous eaters of Fleſh: For the Drunkard and the Glutton ſhall come to Poverty; and drowſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſhall clothe a Man with Rags.</hi> The Spirit of <hi>God</hi> joyns <hi>Sleep</hi> with <hi>Gluttony,</hi> to ſhew us, that it is impoſſible to be a <hi>Glutton</hi> without being <hi>ſlothful.</hi> The hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vineſs of Meats communicates it ſelf to the Stomach, and the heavineſs of the Stomach reacheth the very Brain: No wonder then that by theſe ſeveral <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vineſſes</hi> the Soul becomes heavy, and leſs apt to perform the Functions to which ſhe is deſigned. The <hi>Slothful Perſon</hi> has but juſt the Senſe and Motion of a Man; and of that he hath ſo little, that there
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:133315:25"/>is not much difference between him and a Statue. This never ſtirs but when he is carried; and he never acts without being ſpurred forwards. The ſlowneſs of all his Actions both Spiritual and Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreal, is a ſort of <hi>Lethargy</hi> both of <hi>Soul</hi> and <hi>Body,</hi> whereof he would not be cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red tho it might be done, becauſe his delight is in a ſlothful Eaſe; and the thoughts of a moderate Labour, which is a pleaſure to others, to him is a tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. St. <hi>Paul</hi> may cry out long enough to him, that <hi>he who will not work muſt not eat:</hi> there muſt be ſomething more ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous than the bare Exhortation of the Apoſtle; for Neceſſity it ſelf (tho a thing ſo prevailing) can ſcarce rouſe him out of that Idleneſs, whoſe ſweets are more ſenſible to him than all the Advantages that might accrue from an honeſt Employment. He doth not act with more Zeal for his Intereſt in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven than for that upon Earth; whereby you may judge, that if he is <hi>not a good Citizen,</hi> he is as <hi>ill a Chriſtian;</hi> and you may believe that as the <hi>Glutton</hi> has not made <hi>Temperance</hi> a guide to his Actions, ſo neither has the <hi>Sluggard</hi> conſulted
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:133315:25"/>
                  <hi>Fortitude</hi> to govern <hi>his.</hi> One of the chief Motives of your Voyage (as you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted to me) was, that you might in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe your Fortune through your own means; but you ſee <hi>Sloth</hi> cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to a Deſign ſo honeſt and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable. <hi>He becometh poor that dealeth with a ſlack Hand; but the hand of the Diligent maketh rich.</hi> If you would have me believe your Intentions to be ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, be diligent; and therefore in the firſt place, do your utmoſt endeavours to maſter that great ſweetneſs and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure which you find in Sleep. Never ſtay to be importuned to follow your Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment; yet if you muſt be called up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, let it be done by your own Honour, which leading you every Morning to your Buſineſs, may alſo keep you to it the greateſt part of the Day, with an aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiduity worthy of Praiſe. You need not wonder, <hi>my Son,</hi> that I do encounter ſo obſtinately this Sin of Sloth with all the Arms that the Kindneſs I bear to you can lend me: I am incited thereto not only by that Reaſon I have already told you, but alſo becauſe it is the Path to another deadly Sin, whereto we are naturally ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:133315:26"/>much enclined; to wit, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs,</hi> the moſt foul of any Sin, which changeth our Bodies that ought to be the <hi>Temples</hi> of the <hi>Holy Ghost</hi> into <hi>ſtinking Jakes.</hi> I will deſcribe it to you in few Words, not to keep you long upon the conſideration of what is ſo loathſom, the Name whereof St. <hi>Paul</hi> would not have to be pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced among Chriſtians, and which he terms the blackeſt of Sins, <hi>becauſe,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>every Sin which a Man doth is without the Body; but he that committeth Fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſinneth against his own Body.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I would have you obſerve, <hi>my Son,</hi> that from theſe two laſt Vices <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> proceeds, as I intimated to you above: 'Tis begot by <hi>Gluttony,</hi> and hatched by <hi>Idleneſs.</hi> It will not ſeem ſtrange to you that ſuch <hi>evil Parents</hi> engender ſo <hi>wicked</hi> a <hi>Child.</hi> It has it's Inclination from the Authors of its Birth, and even improves their noxious Qualities; for this Vice alone procures us more miſchief than both the others together. In <hi>Gluttony</hi> and <hi>Sloth,</hi> our Bodies ſuffer <hi>before</hi> our Minds; but <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs</hi> ſeiſes and prevails upon our Minds <hi>before</hi> it ſubdues our Bodies; and having made it ſelf Maſter of that which
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:133315:26"/>was given for our Guide, it hurrieth us along to diſhoneſt, and ſhameful Deſires, by a Tyranny both abſolute and inevita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, altho in the fulfilling of thoſe Deſires we meet our utter Deſtruction. This Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my is ſo much the more dangerous, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the <hi>means</hi> wherewith it uſeth to deſtroy us are <hi>Pleaſure</hi> and <hi>Delight,</hi> which lead us aſide from Vertue, and ſtrangle us in their Embraces. By their Cunning they ſeduce us; they charm us with their Complaiſance; and ſo ſtraight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly engage us to them, that of our ſelves 'tis impoſſible we ſhould break the Chains wherewith they faſten us. They are ſo many <hi>Dalila's</hi> who lull us aſleep, that they may firſt deprive us of our Strength, and then tumble us into the bottomleſs Pit of all Vices. They draw us and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice us to our everlaſting Ruin, if we do not prevent them by a ſerious Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, which if too late, might be in vain. Shun then ſuch Guides under whoſe Conduct the Event will be ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy. Fly from <hi>them</hi> with more ſpeed than you would from <hi>Robbers</hi> on the High-way; for theſe will be contented with your <hi>Money</hi> and <hi>Clothes,</hi> but the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:133315:27"/>others aim directly at your <hi>Soul</hi> and <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. My Son,</hi> you may obſerve theſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections with much more eaſe, if you do but conſider, that all Pleaſures taking advantage of our weakneſs, faſten us to them with a promiſe of the ſweeteſt Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factions, which at laſt prove to be but bitter Sorrows. In this they are like <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban,</hi> who perceiving <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Affection, engaged him to ſerve ſeven Years for <hi>beautiful Rachel,</hi> and when that term was expired gave him only <hi>ill-favoured Leah.</hi> Theſe Directions, I ſay, you may more eaſily follow, if you will diligently obſerve how filthy, baſe, and infamous are theſe very Pleaſures which our <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs</hi> makes uſe of to ſeduce us; how ſoon they paſs away; what Miſchiefs at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend them; and laſtly, the Pains we muſt undergo <hi>to all Eternity,</hi> for thoſe Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures that laſted but <hi>one Hour,</hi> or perhaps but <hi>one Moment. Temperance</hi> will make you avoid theſe Dangers, if you take its Advice, and after that it has demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to you that whilſt <hi>they command you</hi> they are full of danger; it will make you alſo confeſs that they are innocent and harmleſs when <hi>you can command them,</hi> and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:133315:27"/>purge them from the Venom they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted with the Impurity of their Birth; for having taken away all the Means whereby they might be hurtful to us, we may make them to be ſerviceable againſt their own Nature, to our honeſt and lawful Recreations.</p>
               <p>There remains yet behind, <hi>my Son,</hi> the two Sins of <hi>Anger</hi> and <hi>Envy.</hi> The firſt of theſe caſts a man into the greateſt exceſs of Diſorder. It drives from our Minds all manner of Reaſon; and as ſoon as ever it ſeizeth the Heart, it filleth it with Motions ſo violent and tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuous, that it is very fitly termed a <hi>ſhort Madneſs.</hi> Fury and Brutiſhneſs are the two chief Branches that ſpring from it: And I think you need but behold the Actions of a Man enflamed with Anger to acknowledge this Truth; they are ſo many irrefragable Proofs of it; for if his Words did not ſpeak him a Man, there's no Body but would take him for ſome fierce Wild Beaſt. His Soul which is toſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to and fro with thoſe violent and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly Motions, doth expreſs her Agitation ſo plain in the Features and Lineaments
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:133315:28"/>of his Countenance, that it is no hard matter to know by theſe <hi>outward Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters</hi> what vexatious Diſorders he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goes <hi>within.</hi> By ſuch innocent Means as theſe, a Learned Man in our time found what he had vainly ſearched after in all the Secrets of Philoſophy; the way to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh the Inclination which one of his Diſciples had towards this Vice, in whoſe vertuous Education he was very much concerned. He ſhewed him in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of a Man agitated with this Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſo great a change, and ſo vaſtly dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from what it was wont to be, that from the <hi>Effects</hi> running up to the <hi>Cauſe,</hi> it was not difficult for him to make him underſtand that a <hi>Stream ſo infected</hi> muſt needs proceed from a <hi>poiſon'd Spring;</hi> whereby he brought him to be ſo averſe from this Vice, that it even diminiſhed extremely the Inclination he had towards it. The <hi>Lacedaemonians</hi> did heretofore uſe the like device to make Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs odious to their Children: They made their Slaves drink to Exceſs, and then they were brought before them in that Condition, who ſeeing them reel and ſtagger, and act like Men depriv'd
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:133315:28"/>of their Senſes, conceived ſo great a ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred for this loathſom Vice, that they would never after be reconciled to it. Do you, <hi>my Son,</hi> take the ſame Method to oppoſe and conquer that Paſſion of Anger, which is a ſort of Drunkenneſs that aſſaults our Underſtanding and clouds our Reaſon with Fumes more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous than thoſe of Wine, becauſe they are of a longer continuance, and they produce more direful Effects. In a word, to give you an eaſie and infallible Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy againſt Anger, tho you have ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo great Provocations thereto; pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe the Advice of a great Perſon of this latter Age, who exhorts us to yield betimes <hi>to Reaſon,</hi> that which in a little while we cannot but yield <hi>to Time.</hi> To this wholſom Advice add <hi>Fortitude,</hi> that Heroick Vertue, and the ſupport of the reſt, whereof <hi>Prudence</hi> is the Guide, and it will not be difficult for you to ſucced.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Envy</hi> is the laſt Vice I have to mention, whoſe Picture I am going to draw. Of all Vices 'tis the moſt rampant. It inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Man to a Crime which being direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed immediately againſt <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Nature,</hi>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:133315:29"/>made him fail in his Duty <hi>to one</hi> and <hi>t'other;</hi> and in one Act made him com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit Sacrilege and Murder, by ſtirring up <hi>Cain</hi> to deface the Image of <hi>God</hi> in the Perſon of his Brother whom he killed. 'Tis a Paſſion which after having poiſon'd the Mind, ſpreads alſo it's Poiſon all over the Body; which corrupts the whole Maſs of Blood, and caſteth its Venome through all the Veins; which renders the Countenance <hi>meager, ghaſtly, hideous,</hi> and which notwithſtanding all Endeavours to lye hid, doth manifeſtly expoſe it ſelf by disfiguring that Perſon whom it poſſeſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: And we may very juſtly ſay, that if <hi>Anger</hi> is a Fire which enflames us, <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy</hi> is one that dries us up, and carrieth along with it the Puniſhment of the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious,</hi> ſeeing that neither Night nor Day doth it ſuffer him to take any Reſt. 'Tis like a Hecktick Fever which conſumes a Mans Body by degrees, and which is dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult to drive away, when through Neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence one has ſuffer'd it to take Root. The <hi>Envious</hi> Man ſtrikes directly at <hi>God.</hi> He derives his greateſt Miſery from the juſt diſtribution <hi>God</hi> makes of his Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits to other men. Another's Calamity is
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:133315:29"/>his Joy. The good Health of his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour diminiſheth his own, and his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour falling ſick makes him well again. His Draughts are then <hi>ſweetest</hi> when mingled with the <hi>bitter Tears</hi> of his Neighbour. His private Sorrows ariſe from the Satisfaction and Content of the Publick. He looks upon that Gain or Profit that doth not help fill up <hi>his</hi> Bags, to be a great loſs to <hi>himſelf;</hi> and he is never happy but in the miſery of thoſe of his Acquaintance. The moderate Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt of another makes his own unaccepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, tho it be abundant; and the greateſt Proſperity in this World would be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>welcome to him, if he were forced to ſhare ſome part of it with his Neighbours. You may eaſily perceive, <hi>my Son,</hi> that a Man of this Temper can have Peace with no body, and that generally he muſt be at War with <hi>God:</hi> judge thereby of the Tranquility of his Body and Soul. Others comprehend their Unhappineſs within their own Calamities; but the Envious, beſides their own peculiar Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes, procure to themſelves an infinite number from the good Fortune of others. Shun therefore this Vice which is ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:133315:30"/>and deteſtable, that it is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for any one to be guilty of it without becoming both a Puniſhment to himſelf and his own Executioner. And be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that after it has furiouſly tormented in this Life thoſe who are poſſeſſed with it, in the next it will lead them into that Place which <hi>Divine Juſtice</hi> has ſet apart for all thoſe who have not a ſubmiſſive regard to whatſoever is ordained by <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Deſcription I have made to you of theſe Vices has been ſomething longer than I ſhould have imagined. <hi>God</hi> grant the Style may be not only ſo clear as to excite in you that Hatred which you ought to have againſt them, but alſo ſo perſuaſive as to encourage you in the Love and Practice of their oppoſite Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues. There is not any thing can be throughly known until it be compared with its contrary; if therefore you have apprehended the Reaſons which ſhould move you to hate <hi>Pride, Covetouſneſs, Gluttony, Sloth, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs, Anger,</hi> and <hi>Envy;</hi> you will eaſily be perſuaded for the Welfare of your Soul and Body, to
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:133315:30"/>love <hi>Humility, a liberal Frugality, Sobrie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Diligence, Chaſtity, Moderation,</hi> and <hi>Charity;</hi> and to poſſeſs theſe Vertues you muſt take <hi>your Meaſures</hi> from the Dictates of <hi>Prudence, Fortitude,</hi> and <hi>Temperance,</hi> whoſe Counſels cannot but be advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous to you, if you will thereunto ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieſce. Among all the Benefits that you may receive from theſe Vertues, I would to <hi>God, my Son,</hi> they would inſpire you with as much Love for <hi>Truth,</hi> as young People have Inclination for <hi>Lying.</hi> Have in Horror this Vice; and to do this eaſily, remember that JESUS CHRIST took upon him this Quality of <hi>True,</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſignifie to us that he loved thoſe who loved the <hi>Truth:</hi> And why (think you) is the <hi>Devil</hi> termed in the Scripture <hi>the Father of Lies,</hi> unleſs it be to ſhew that <hi>all Lyars</hi> are his Children? The love of this Vice is an undeniable Character upon all thoſe who practiſe it through In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination, (and from this Inclination ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire a Habit) that they are the Children of the <hi>Devil.</hi> I know very well that they who are willing to excuſe it, ſay, that a ſecret Shame which they have, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge themſelves guilty of the Fault
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:133315:31"/>imputed to them, doth not ſeldom drive them againſt their Will into a Neceſſity of Lying. It is an <hi>ill Preſident</hi> that <hi>Adam</hi> hath left to his Poſterity: But what ſignifie all theſe Prevarications wherewith we diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble the Truth? They are but like <hi>ſo many Fig-leaves</hi> through which the Truth <hi>will</hi> be diſcerned in ſpight of all our Endeavours to the contrary. The Hopes of a more regular Conduct hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter doth ſomewhat comfort thoſe who are concerned for their preſent Indiſcretion; but daily Experience teacheth us, that when a Man has committed a Fault, and that he endeavours to evade it with a Lye, he is leſs ſorry for <hi>being guilty</hi> than for <hi>being ſo reputed.</hi> I do not pretend, <hi>my Son,</hi> by exhorting you never to lye, to publiſh and declare whatever you know to be true; this in <hi>many</hi> Caſes would be a great Imprudence; yet Lying is a Crime in <hi>all:</hi> the beſt way to avoid it is to ſpeak little and live well. A Man needs not uſe Diſſimulation if his Conduct is good; and he is always ſincere in his Diſcourſe that conſiders firſt what he is about to ſay, and then conſults <hi>Prudence,</hi> the Definition whereof will convince you
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:133315:31"/>of it. 'Tis a Habit of the Underſtanding which preſcribes to our Deſires, means both honeſt and convenient to attain a favourable and happy End. You may eaſily perceive then, that how profitable ſoever are the Ends you propoſe to your ſelf in your Undertakings, the means cannot be honourable if you make uſe of Deceit and Lying to compaſs them. Your Hatred towards this Vice will not only cauſe you to be more reſerved in your Speech, it will render you alſo more cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpect in all your Actions, and (by grafting Sincerity in your Heart) will make you abhor Detraction and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumny, two general Plagues, whence ſpring moſt of our Troubles, they being often the Cauſe of our Quarrels. Since<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is always attended with Probity; and one and t'other are as abſolutely neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in <hi>Pious Duties,</hi> as in <hi>thoſe</hi> of <hi>Society.</hi> You cannot be a good Chriſtian without being an honeſt Man, neither can you be an honeſt Man if you are deceitful. Diſſimulation is a <hi>Sacrilege in Religion,</hi> and Lying is almoſt as great a <hi>Crime in Converſation.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:133315:32"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>My Son,</hi> whatſoever Profeſſion you fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, let Vertue and Induſtry be your Guides, and not Pleaſure and Idleneſs. The Idle and the Voluptuous, from Men are transformed into Beaſts, and by a <hi>Metamorphoſis</hi> ſo much the more ſhameful as that they willingly conſent to it. <hi>My Son,</hi> if you would have your Affairs ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, never undertake what is above your Capacity, nor what you do not throughly underſtand. Moreover, let the means, whereby you intend to obtain your Ends, be moſt honeſt and juſt: yet how juſt ſoever thoſe means are, and how exact your Knowledge in what you undertake, begin nothing till you have begged God's Bleſſing upon your Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizes; your Cares and Induſtry, tho ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo great, would be needleſs, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps a hinderance to your Affairs, if this Bleſſing did not intervene and render them happy. If notwithſtanding all theſe <hi>Precautions,</hi> Providence is not pleaſed that the Succeſs ſhould anſwer your De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, fail not however to praiſe his Holy Name, and ſubmit to his Will with a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectful and implicite Faith; aſſuring your ſelf that it had <hi>not</hi> ſo happened, if <hi>other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe,</hi>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:133315:32"/>it might have been better for <hi>his</hi> Glory, or <hi>your</hi> Salvation.</p>
               <p>Take hold, with a <hi>judicious</hi> eagerneſs, of all favourable Opportunities which your Good Fortune offers you: They are rare now-a-days, and much ſearched after; be careful that you let them not ſlip when you meet any, leſt when they are gone, you follow after them to no purpoſe.</p>
               <p>Make good Uſe of your Time, for what you loſe thereof can never be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered. New Gains may over and above ſupply old Loſſes, but the Loſs of Time is irrecoverable.</p>
               <p>By exhorting you to apply your ſelf to your Buſineſs, I do not mean that you ſhould give up your ſelf ſo entirely to it, as to receive <hi>no Diverſion.</hi> I am ſenſible that as the Body cannot long un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo Labour, ſo neither can the Mind be engaged in a moderate Study, if a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Relaxation of their Functions yield not to both of them the Means to repair the Strength and Spirits which they loſt. For this Reaſon I ſhall be ſo far from <hi>forbidding</hi> you Recreations, that I adviſe you to uſe them, nevertheleſs with this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:133315:33"/>to chooſe, as near as you can gueſs, ſuch as are the moſt honeſt and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent. I take thoſe Diverſions whereby the Body is moderately exerciſed to be the more proper of the two for a Chriſtian and an Honeſt Man, than Gaming, which depends upon much Hazard. But as in this Caſe, Choice depends upon Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, you would do well to make yours (as much as you can) <hi>ſubſervient to your Duty,</hi> which will put you in mind that, let the Game be what it will, you ought to be very careful in this Occaſion, not to render Principal what ſhould be but Acceſſary. Let your Game therefore be a delightful Recreation, and not a vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atious Trouble, ſuch as might be occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned by a great Loſs, if you hazard any conſiderable Sums. Never put it to the venture to quit that with a Grudge which you began for your Diverſion; and this cannot be, if you play but for Play-ſake, that is, if you play but for a Small matter, and with the intent only to refreſh your Spirits, which an Exceſs of Buſineſs and Study had tryed: How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever let the Sum be never ſo inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable for which you play, take heed it
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:133315:33"/>be with ſuch as you know, that they may not firſt Cheat, and then Deride you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ignorance</hi> and <hi>Preſumption</hi> have poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the World almoſt from the Creation: Avoid both with Care. Seek therefore <hi>my Son,</hi> to be inſtructed, and be not aſhamed to ask the Council of thoſe who know more than your ſelf. Be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways miſtruſtful of your own Parts, and never take it ill from thoſe who give you their Advice, but rather receive it with all imaginable Sweetneſs and Reſpect, <hi>reſerving only</hi> to your ſelf the Freedom of following it, if you find it conſonat to <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Prudence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Love <hi>Reading;</hi> 'tis that which <hi>ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens the Judgment, enriches the Memory,</hi> and <hi>enlightens</hi> every Day more and more the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding.</hi> 'Tis that which will teach us to expreſs our ſelves in a Style ſublime, tho both Smooth and Charming: ſo that we may ſay, 'tis that alone procures us all the Advantages neceſſary, either in Meditation or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe. Yet do not read only to be ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd more knowing, read chiefly to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:133315:34"/>better; and to that End make choice of good Books, applying your ſelf moſt commonly to ſuch as treat of <hi>Piety,</hi> in the reading whereof, ſet before you the Example of the Bee, which ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>there the ſweet Dew out of Flowers to make Honey in it's due Seaſon. Now to profit by this Example, obſerve that when you read, (whether they be Books of <hi>Devotion, Morality</hi> or <hi>Hiſtory</hi>) you do not neglect the reducing under Heads in a Common-place, the excellent Notes and Obſervations that you will collect: that will <hi>eaſe</hi> very much your Memory, and in many occaſions will ſave you the trouble (which muſt otherwiſe lie upon you) of ſearching after Expreſſions, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of you may ſtand in Need.</p>
               <p>Do not imploy your Time in <hi>reading Romances:</hi> They only heat the Imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and not nouriſh the Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; for altho they repreſent Vertues in their higheſt Degree, nevertheleſs there lies a great deal of <hi>Venome</hi> hid under thoſe lovely Flowers, eſpecially for young People. You will do well to let alone the Reading of ſuch Books, which
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:133315:34"/>are Snares ſo much the more difficult to avoid, as being in <hi>appearence</hi> not dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, tho in <hi>reality</hi> they are much.</p>
               <p>Take ſpecial heed, <hi>my Son,</hi> that the deſire of Riches doth not force you up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on evil Means to obtain them, nor excite you to Actions Mercinary, Baſe and Unjuſt. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe not divers Weights, and divers Meaſures; both of them are alike Abomination to the Lord. Better is a little with Righteouſneſs, then great Revenues without Right.</hi> And remember, that <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyneſs with Contentment is great Gain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Shun <hi>Ambition,</hi> tho ſome only call it an Errour of great Minds. I always con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd it as proceeding from Minds vain and defective. 'Tis a Monſter moſt unſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiable, whoſe Deſigns are without Limits as well as his Hopes, and how ſucceſsful ſoever is the Ambitious in his Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizes, the Succeſs doth rather puff up his Deſires than content them. His Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement to an eminent Employment which he expected, diſcovers to him ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more Eminent, without which his Happineſs ſeems to be imperfect. As
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:133315:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>faſt as his Honour and Grandure <hi>encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> his Hopes and Pretentions <hi>multiply:</hi> The whole World can ſcarce ſatisfie him: Like <hi>Pompey,</hi> he will have no Equal, much leſs can he endure a Superiour. His Life paſſeth in a perpetual Hurry of Body and Mind. Tranquility and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe are <hi>Terrae incognitae</hi> to him; and it often happens, that the Care he has been at to place himſelf ſo high, ſerves to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his <hi>fall</hi> the more irrecoverable. Come not therefore near a Road ſo dangerous, where inſtead of repoſing your ſelf you will find nothing but dreadful Precipices.</p>
               <p>If any one ſpread an ill Report of you, and that it comes to your knowledge, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine it <hi>impartially;</hi> and if you find your ſelf guilty of that which is imputed to you, mend, and be thankful to him who did you this good Office. If you are blamed wrongfully ſhew no Anger or Diſpleaſure; for Experience makes it manifeſt to us daily, that the <hi>Contempt</hi> of <hi>Calumny</hi> makes it die, whereas nothing but a Reſentment can keep it alive.</p>
               <p>A learned Man of theſe Times ſaid, that all Vertues were ſwallowed up in Intereſt, like the Rivers in the Sea. Avoid, <hi>my Son,</hi>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:133315:35"/>this <hi>ſelfiſh</hi> Humor, which aiming ſo much at our own Advantage, makes us forget what in Juſtice is due to others. Accommodate your Intereſt to Reaſon, and to that Law of Nature, which was an ancient Maxim among Pagans; <hi>Do not to others, what you would not that they ſhould do unto you;</hi> or rather to this Chriſtian Doctrine, <hi>do as you would be done by.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Be careful not to take Exceptions; of a Trifle do not make a Buſineſs of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, no more then of a Buſineſs of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment a Trifle. Labour to be in Peace with all Men; and rather relinquiſh ſomething of your Right, than to enter into a Conteſt with any one. What ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in this Caſe would call, <hi>parting with his Poſſeſſions to ſatiate the Greedineſs of his Neighbour,</hi> do you conſider as an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument to conſerve the Tranquility of your Mind, and the Repoſe of your Body, which you ought to eſteem be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all Wealth and Poſſeſſions.</p>
               <p>Never put off to a Future Time, that which you can do at the Preſent. Do every thing in Order, avoiding all Confuſion, and let this Order be ſeen as
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:133315:36"/>well in your Clothes, as in your Books; as well in your ſmalleſt Papers, as in your moſt conſiderable Affairs.</p>
               <p>Regulate your Expences by your E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, and if that Eſtate will permit, do not deny your ſelf any thing that is Fitting, but have a Care you delight not in what is <hi>Superfluous,</hi> leſt inſenſibly you become unable to provide for your ſelf things abſolutely <hi>Neceſſary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Altho the Neceſſity of Clothing was one Conſequence of the firſt Sin of <hi>Adam,</hi> there are not a few Perſons that make it one of the chief Subjects of their Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and one of the moſt painful Cares of their Life. <hi>Garments,</hi> which are only to preſerve our Bodies from the injury of Weather, and which for this Reaſon ought to be ordain'd to no other Uſe, are leaſt of all for that Uſe among thoſe ſort of People: They have them to ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie their immoderate Deſires, as well as to ſhelter their Bodies from the Intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the Seaſons. This is a Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in either Sex, and 'tis <hi>Intolerable in both;</hi> however, 'tis <hi>much more</hi> to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd in Men then in Women, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe moſt Women making their Merit
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:133315:36"/>conſiſt in an <hi>exteriour Comelineſs,</hi> you need not wonder if they ſeek to make themſelves prized by the Magnificence of their Habits, and by the Beauty and Excellency of their Trimmings, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as Men, who ought to be more reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſhould deſpiſe (as below them) theſe vile ſordid Means to make themſelves be taken notice of; and only render themſelves conſiderable by <hi>Vertue,</hi> and their <hi>Excellent Qualifications.</hi> To this I muſt exhort you with all earneſtneſs; however, in the Order you obſerve for your Apparel, I would wiſh you to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe with your own Eſtate, to conſider what is decent, and chiefly to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to what is moſt reaſonable. If you do this your Habit will be always far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt from Extremes; you will be <hi>neat</hi> and not affected, <hi>well Clothed</hi> and not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant.</p>
               <p>Be neither the <hi>firſt</hi> nor the <hi>laſt</hi> in fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the <hi>Mode;</hi> too much Compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with all Faſhions is ridiculous, as on the other ſide too be always thwart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Mode, is to be obſtinate and Fantaſtical. Shun alike both theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremes, and by obſerving a Mean, let
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:133315:37"/>People rather applaud your Modeſty than condemn your Conceitedneſs. Be eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>rather</hi> for your perſonal Qualifications, than for your external Ornaments; in a Word, be <hi>more</hi> diligent in beautify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your <hi>Soul</hi> with good Qualities, than in adorning your <hi>Body</hi> with rich Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel.</p>
               <p>Whatſoever you ſpeak, or whatſoever you write, let it be in Words few but comprehenſive, ſo that much may be contained in a little; yet not withſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you have free, ſmooth, and graceful Expreſſions in <hi>your</hi> Diſcourſe, let it be a Pleaſure to you when you are in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany to hearken attentively to <hi>their</hi> Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and to anſwer them appoſitely and to the purpoſe, that you may gain their good Will and Affection: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore remember this, that Converſation is not like a <hi>Monarchical Government,</hi> where <hi>one</hi> has only a right to ſpeak; but rather a kind of <hi>Democracy,</hi> where each Member has a Freedom of declaring their Minds in <hi>their turn.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secrecy</hi> is the Soul of a Deſign, and not ſeldom the ſole occaſion of it's Succeſs: The more important are your Deſigns,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:133315:37"/>the greater ought your Care to be in concealing them from others; yet if they are never ſo inconſiderable, 'tis beſt to make no Body acquainted with them. Without this Precaution, me thinks you ſhould be afraid leſt it happen as it doth often to Mines, whoſe Effects terminate but in Smoak when once they have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Wind.</p>
               <p>Fly from <hi>Idleneſs;</hi> 'tis a ſort of <hi>Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Lethargy,</hi> ſo much the more dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, as that the <hi>End</hi> of it is generally the <hi>Beginning</hi> of ſome Diſorder. Man was created to be always acting; and of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity he muſt always be employed; therefore if his Actions are not good, they infallibly tend to Evil: And <hi>Idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> has this Reſemblance with <hi>Standing Waters,</hi> that if <hi>theſe</hi> breed Serpents <hi>t'other</hi> breeds Vices.</p>
               <p>There are many People who are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme eager to know what is done in <hi>their Neighbour's Houſe,</hi> and at the ſame time are ignorant of moſt things that happen in <hi>their own.</hi> This Curioſity has always ſeem'd to me to be pityful and baſe, and unworthy of an honeſt Man: Therefore to avoid it, conſider
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:133315:38"/>with your ſelf that he into whoſe affairs you are prying is ether a <hi>Friend,</hi> or elſe is <hi>indifferent</hi> to you: If he is <hi>indifferent,</hi> what ſatisfaction can you propoſe by knowing what he aims at? And if he is your <hi>Friend,</hi> why would you ſearch into a Secret, which his Silence ſignifies he has a Mind to keep from you?</p>
               <p>It belongs only to Kings to ſay that he who cannot diſſemble knows not how to reign. <hi>Diſſimulation,</hi> tho <hi>ſometimes</hi> a Vertue in a <hi>Soverain Prince,</hi> is <hi>always</hi> a Vice in the <hi>Subject.</hi> Yet there are ſome Caſes wherein it is a part of Prudence not to publiſh and make known all we think. But upon ſuch like Occaſions as theſe, be ſo much reſerved, that by your ſpeaking you may not be taxed with <hi>Indiſcretion,</hi> nor by your Silence with <hi>Diſſimulation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When you happen into Company where there are ſome that you don't know, be careful not to fall into that <hi>vulgar Errour</hi> of paſſing your Judgment upon the Merit of Perſons by their <hi>rich Clothes,</hi> or the <hi>fine Style</hi> of their Diſcourſe. Theſe Appearances are very doubtful, and it is often mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted by Experience, that thoſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:133315:38"/>are not the moſt worthy becauſe they are the beſt clothed, nor are the moſt Vertuous always the moſt eloquent: Therefore, <hi>my Son,</hi> in ſuch a Caſe let not your Mind be anticipated; let your Judgment decide nothing <hi>without</hi> your Knowledge, and be ſure you <hi>Penetrate beyond</hi> the outward Parts of a Man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you judge well or ill of him.</p>
               <p>Flattery is the ſame to the <hi>Mind</hi> as <hi>Poiſon</hi> is to the <hi>Body,</hi> with this only diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, that all People <hi>hate</hi> Poiſon, yet they all <hi>love</hi> Flattery. The paſſionate Love that every one bears toward it, is a ſort of Leproſie which has infected all the Earth. You ſhall find it in Shepherds poor Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages as well as in the Palaces of Kings. 'Tis true it reigns among <hi>Kings and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> with more Oſtentation then among <hi>the People,</hi> which produceth Events ſo much the more pernicious, according to the Power of that Perſon whom it affects. Proſperity is the Mother of Flattery as <hi>Intereſt</hi> is the ſole Object of Flatterers; and for this Reaſon alone there are more in the Courts of Princes than among pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Families, who yet are not wholly exempt, the moſt miſerable of all Men
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:133315:39"/>having at leaſt <hi>one</hi> who keeps hin com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany all his Life-time, and who becomes <hi>ſo Familiar</hi> to him, that inſenſibly he uſhers in all forreign Flaterrers. <hi>My Son,</hi> I find that you eagerly expect to know the <hi>Name</hi> of this Flatterer; I will tell it you then: 'Tis <hi>Self-love;</hi> who <hi>introduces</hi> all our Errours, who <hi>corrupts</hi> our Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>darkens</hi> our Underſtanding; and laſtly <hi>disfigures</hi> Truth ſo ſtrangely that it is impoſſible for us to know her. Let therefore this Deſcription I have given you of the Effects produced by <hi>Flattery,</hi> cauſe in you a <hi>miſtruſt</hi> as well of the Domeſtick as the Forreign Flatterrer; let this foreknowledg of them break all their Meaſures, and thereby preſerve you from being enchanted with thoſe poiſon'd ſweets which being once inſtill'd into you, will infallibly carry it's Venom to your very Heart.</p>
               <p>I am now, <hi>my Son,</hi> come to an Article <hi>delicate, important,</hi> and <hi>difficult</hi> to han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, which I would not willingly omit, that it might not be ſaid I had paſſed over in Silence any thing that could con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to your Inſtruction. 'Tis then concerning, how you muſt carry your
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:133315:39"/>ſelf, if in unlucky and unexpected diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences you are obliger to declare your ſelf of any Party. If I went about to treat of this one Point to it's greateſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, it would require a Volume much larger than the whole Treatiſe I deſign for you, which is <hi>contrary</hi> to the Purpoſe I intended, of rendring you <hi>rather</hi> an Honeſt than a Learned Man. 'Tis enough for you to obſerve theſe two or three Rules which I am going to give you. The Differences of this Nature are either <hi>publick</hi> or <hi>private;</hi> of which ſort ſoever they are, 'tis beſt for you not to meddle if you can chooſe, unleſs you ſee apparently that you can be <hi>ſo happy</hi> as to contribute towards a Re-union. But if you cannot poſſibly ſtand Neuter, and that an unavoidable Neceſſity obligeth you to ſide with a Party; in that Caſe I earneſtly exhort you to take this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel I now give you. If the Buſineſs in queſtion be publick, and that the <hi>Prince</hi>'s <hi>Interest</hi> is concerned, adhere immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly without any manner of Scruple to <hi>his</hi> Party. You preſerve <hi>God's Right</hi> in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending the lawful Authority of Kings, who are <hi>his Vicegerents;</hi> and the <hi>Holy
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:133315:40"/>Ghost</hi> has ſo interwoven the Intereſts of <hi>thoſe</hi> that reign with the Intereſts <hi>of him</hi> by whom they reign, that he ſaith, <hi>Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever reſiſteth Power reſiſteth God.</hi> It is far better <hi>to dye</hi> for your Prince, than by uſurping <hi>to reign</hi> in his Place. In this Caſe fail not to follow <hi>your Duty,</hi> without reflecting in the leaſt upon what would be moſt for <hi>your Advantage;</hi> and <hi>venture all</hi> that you have in the World, if there is any Probability that it will produce advantageous Effects for the <hi>Royal Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest.</hi> But if on the other ſide it is only a private Grudge or Animoſity between ſome few; before you declare your ſelf for either Party, conſider impartially whoſe Cauſe is moſt juſt: which you may eaſily perceive; for without any doubt the Right is on their Side with whom the greateſt Number of Perſons of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, Integrity, and Diſcretion take part. Eſpouſe therefore that Cauſe: neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs keep within the Bounds of Moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and be not too forward in meddling with their Affairs, eſpecially when they proceed to Heat and Violence, and have no Hand in any Diſorders or injurious Attempts, which they might poſſibly
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:133315:40"/>commit: But rather labour all you can to mollifie thoſe paſſionate and turbulent Spirits, to allay their Heats, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce them to ſuch a Temper of Mind as might prevent the evil Conſequences which would infallibly follow from their Diſ-union with the oppoſite Party. I am ſenſible that neither your Birth nor Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit can make a Party any whit the more conſiderable, but as Accidents may oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur wherein we ſhall be conſtrained (of what Quality ſoever we are) to declare our Intentions tho never ſo much againſt our Will: I thought in ſuch a Rencoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter theſe Inſtructions would be not a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle neceſſary.</p>
               <p>One of the moſt pleaſing Satisfactions that we can have in this World is to be in good Eſteem and Reputation with thoſe of our Acquaintance. This is all we can aim at; for therein is <hi>Honour, Profit,</hi> and <hi>Pleaſure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Be diſcreet and ſincere in all your Words, honeſt and prudent in all your Actions, obliging and affable in all your Behaviour. Never conſtrue ill what others ſay or do, unleſs they come to be publickly ſo cenſur'd.</p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:133315:41"/>
               <p>Take great heed of being revengeful. <hi>Revenge</hi> pierceth and teareth the Heart that is filled therewith. The Grounds that make you deſire <hi>Revenge</hi> are either juſt or injuſt; if injuſt, then you are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt to deſire it; and if juſt, then by en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to revenge your ſelf you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come injuſt; for you encroach upon the Prerogative of the King of Heaven, who hath ſaid, <hi>Vengeance is mine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To avoid <hi>Perjury</hi> or falſe Swearing, which amongſt Men is ſcandalous, and abominable in the ſight of <hi>God;</hi> I adviſe you to ſwear not at all. If you once get a Habit of ſpeaking always Truth every one will eaſily believe you, without any need of affirming it with an Oath.</p>
               <p>Among all Vices, there is none more baſe and yet more ordinary than <hi>Ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude;</hi> this is the general Opinion and Complaint of the World: and if all thoſe who thus complain were free from it, no body would uſe it; for every one complains thereof. The Ancients by a ſpecial Myſtery have limited the <hi>Graces</hi> to the number of <hi>three,</hi> to intimate, that if <hi>one</hi> of them had received a good Turn from the <hi>other,</hi> the <hi>third</hi> was to return it
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:133315:41"/>to her. Make hereof a Law to your ſelf, and an urgent Endeavour to follow this Leſſon, and never to be ungrateful for any, at leaſt conſiderable, Benefit recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
               <p>If you intend my Satisfaction, or your own Quiet, be careful never to become Surety for any Man, for any Cauſe what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever. If your Friend hath need of you, ſerve him with your <hi>Purſe</hi> and <hi>Advice,</hi> with all your Power and Intereſt; but keep <hi>your Liberty,</hi> and engage for no Man. If you have a mind to help a Friend in neceſſity, and that you are well able to do it, do it quickly; but if you are not well able, why will you bind your ſelf to do it hereafter, when perhaps you ſhall be leſs able? Therefore <hi>be not bound</hi> for any unleſs you care not to be <hi>rid</hi> of <hi>your Money, your Quiet,</hi> and <hi>your Friend.</hi> In other things, <hi>my Son,</hi> I have been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to adviſe you, to exhort and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade you; but herein I make uſe of all Authority which the Quality of Father gives me, and do <hi>abſolutely forbid</hi> this thing. Take heed of refuſing my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, as you will avoid the Puniſhment which your Diſobedience ſhall juſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve.</p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:133315:42"/>
               <p>Perhaps this may ſeem ſomewhat ſtrange and hard to many Men; yet it is drawn from the Advice of a Great King, who was the wiſeſt Man in the World, 22 Chap. of Prov. <hi>Be not thou one of them that ſtrike Hands, or of them that are Sureties for Debts: If thou hast nothing to pay he may lawfully take thy Bed from under thee. My Son,</hi> by his Opinion I can juſtifie the Severity and Unkindneſs that ſome would impute to mine for ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely forbidding you to become Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for any Man.</p>
               <p>You depart hence, ſufficiently ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Truth of our Religion, being able to render a Reaſon of the Hope that is in you to all that ſhall ask it; which I would have you do upon all Occaſions with Reſpect and Reverence, as St. <hi>Peter</hi> exhorts; yet following the Advice of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> avoid always all Diſputes about Religion, for that rather makes more averſe than perſwades; and the earneſt deſire of confuting, or the fear of being vanquiſhed, tranſports very moderate Men ſometimes to dangerous Extremities: Hereby <hi>Charity</hi> is almoſt always wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and <hi>Truth never cleared,</hi> which makes
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:133315:42"/>appear that it may well be ſaid at this time of Controverſies, what the <hi>Apostle</hi> ſaid heretofore of Fables and Genealogies, which are endleſs; <hi>that they beget rather vain and curious Queſtions than Godly Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication,</hi> which conſiſts in the true <hi>Faith</hi> the <hi>Foundation</hi> of Chriſtian Vertues, as <hi>Charity</hi> is the <hi>Perfection,</hi> and <hi>Hope</hi> the <hi>Crown</hi> thereof: Whereof the firſt hath none but <hi>God</hi> for it's Object, the laſt aims only at <hi>our Selves,</hi> and the middlemoſt contains our Duty to <hi>God,</hi> to <hi>our Selves,</hi> and to <hi>our Neighbour;</hi> for by <hi>Charity</hi> we learn <hi>all</hi> the Duties of a Spiritual Life, as alſo of a Corporeal, which the Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul</hi> preferreth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>other two</hi> Chriſtian Vertues, where he ſaith, <hi>that there abideth Faith, Hope, and Charity, theſe three; but the greateſt of theſe is Charity. God is Love, and he that dwelleth in Love, dwelleth in God, and God in him.</hi> The <hi>other</hi> Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues draw us nearer unto <hi>God,</hi> but <hi>this</hi> renders us like unto him in ſome man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, ſeeing that he accounts it one of his chiefeſt Attributes, that of <hi>Charity;</hi> which is alſo the inexhauſtible Spring of all the Benefits he beſtows upon Man: So that,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:133315:43"/>
                  <hi>my Son,</hi> as often as you are charitable, you will imitate God in one of his moſt frequent Actions, who is never weary of doing good to us, tho we are ſo unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of it. <hi>Do good therefore to all, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to thoſe who are of the Houſhold of Faith:</hi> Yet make not that a Pretext to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold your <hi>Charity</hi> from all thoſe who are not of the ſame Communion with you. All Men are your <hi>Brothers in God;</hi> which Quality alone ſhould ſuffice to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage you to help them in their Need, to comfort them in their Afflictions, and chiefly to let your Aſſiſtance be as ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and effectual as their Neceſſities are urgent. This will be an infallible Means to draw the <hi>Bleſſings</hi> of <hi>Heaven</hi> upon your <hi>Soul,</hi> your <hi>Perſon,</hi> and your <hi>Actions. He that giveth to the Poor lendeth to the Lord: But whoſo ſtoppeth his Ears at the Cry of the Poor, he ſhall alſo cry himſelf, but ſhall not be heard,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon.</hi> You may therefore ſee what is generally the Fruits of <hi>Charity:</hi> However, let not <hi>Self-intereſt</hi> be the <hi>Motive</hi> which inclines you to be charitable; this Vertue would thereby loſe its excellent Quality; and you might expect in vain the Effects of it, if you
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:133315:43"/>pretend to make a Bargain with <hi>God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty.</hi> 'Tis in <hi>Charity</hi> that all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Vertues terminate, and it ſhall be with the Deſcription of this Divine Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity that I will end this Chapter, which contains the Inſtructions that I was to give you about <hi>Perſonal Duties,</hi> after which there only remains, that I ſhould ſay a Word or two concerning <hi>Civil Duties.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Civil Duties.</head>
               <p>HItherto, <hi>my Son,</hi> I have repreſented unto you your <hi>Duty to God;</hi> as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo what you <hi>owe</hi> to <hi>your ſelf</hi> for <hi>his</hi> ſake, <hi>ſeeing that in him we live, and move, and have our Being;</hi> and that all our Thoughts, Words, and Actions ought to tend to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>God,</hi> as to their Center. It is now time I ſhould make you conſider what you <hi>owe</hi> to <hi>Mankind,</hi> to whom you are faſten'd with the Bonds of a Civil So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety.</p>
               <p>For I would not have you imagine, that you was born for your ſelf alone, there lieth an Obligation upon you of
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:133315:44"/>being a Help to your Neighbour. Soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarineſs is not natural to Man, nay, 'tis even <hi>contrary</hi> to the Will and Deſign of the Creator, who plac'd him in the World for <hi>Society-ſake.</hi> Reaſon was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him to no other Purpoſe but to make uſe of it. He has Vertues; he ought to put them in practice: Which he cannot do but with thoſe of his own kind, and in a civil Converſe. In this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, I would have you uſe the <hi>ſubtlety</hi> of the <hi>Serpent,</hi> and yet act with the <hi>ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity</hi> of the <hi>Dove.</hi> Be juſt and ſincere, and have always in your Mind this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Law of Nature which I cited once before; <hi>Do not to others, what you would not that others ſhould do to you.</hi> This Law is not onely a Dictate of Nature, and receiv'd generally throughout the Univerſe; but <hi>God</hi> himſelf makes it a part of <hi>his</hi> Law, when he commands us to love our Neighbour as our ſelf.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>My Son,</hi> obſerve this, that <hi>God</hi> doth command you not onely to <hi>love</hi> your Neighbour, but to love him <hi>as your ſelf,</hi> that is to ſay, as heartily, as ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely, and with an Affection as ardent as is poſſible. This Obligation (as you
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:133315:44"/>may ſee) is of a great Extent; but the Goodneſs of <hi>God</hi> extends <hi>much farther:</hi> he relinquiſheth part of <hi>his Right</hi> for our ſakes; for tho he has required our Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction entire to himſelf, yet he looſeth that Obligation, and is willing we ſhould have for one another part of that which he had demanded from us, and retain'd wholly for himſelf. <hi>Here</hi> he ceaſeth his <hi>Jealouſie,</hi> he that takes upon him ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the Name of <hi>Jealous,</hi> and through an Exceſs of Love which he bears towards us, he is ſo far from being angry that our Neighbour has a ſhare in our Affection, that he commands it, and is well pleas'd to create himſelf <hi>Rivals</hi> upon <hi>this Account.</hi> Man is not ſenſible enough of this Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs which is infinite, (as well as the Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence from whence it proceeds,) for of the <hi>three</hi> kinds of Affections preſcribed to us by the Law of <hi>God,</hi> Man for the moſt part maintains <hi>that</hi> which has a Relation to himſelf, taking no Notice of the <hi>other two,</hi> and by an Exceſs of Self-love he fails in that which is due to <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour,</hi> by which Vice he becomes in this World a <hi>Complice</hi> with the <hi>Devil,</hi> and therefore cannot but expect to ſhare with
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:133315:45"/>him his Puniſhment in the <hi>next:</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to avoid this, love others as much as you would have them love you. To this Duty you ought to apply your ſelf very much, as well for your <hi>Advantage</hi> as to render your Life <hi>ſweet and pleaſant.</hi> Who ſpeaks <hi>Love,</hi> ſpeaks <hi>Service, Eſteem, Honour,</hi> in a Word, ſpeaks <hi>all</hi> obliging Condeſcenſions, which Mans Heart al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways inſpires for thoſe Perſons that are <hi>dear</hi> to him. <hi>My Son,</hi> all Men ſhould be dear to you, and he whoſe Houſe touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth yours is <hi>not</hi> more your <hi>Neighbour</hi> than he that dwelleth in another Country. Be officious towards <hi>all:</hi> Loſe no Opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of ſerving <hi>any one.</hi> Add to the Courteſies you beſtow, a <hi>Way</hi> altogether <hi>obliging</hi> in beſtowing them, which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth their Merit; and though the Perſon be never ſo much unknown to you that demands any thing, if you are not in a Capacity of <hi>ſatisfying</hi> him, do not encreaſe his Diſcontent occaſion'd by your <hi>Refuſal,</hi> with harſh and unkind Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage; but rather diminiſh <hi>his</hi> Trouble, by <hi>that</hi> which you ſhould expreſs in <hi>not being ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>able</hi> to content him. This Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct will not only gain <hi>Eſteem,</hi> but alſo
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:133315:45"/>a general <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Affection</hi> whereſoever you happen to be.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Great Perſons</hi> are to us as the <hi>Flame</hi> of <hi>Candles</hi> are to <hi>Flies.</hi> We muſt have a <hi>great care</hi> of approaching them too fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarly, leſt we run in danger of <hi>burning</hi> our ſelves. There is nothing ſo alluring (and yet ſo full of Deceit) as their pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pous Equipage and their ſplendid Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainments. <hi>My Son,</hi> be not dazled with it; and whether they derive their Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs from their <hi>Birth,</hi> or from their <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune,</hi> let only their Vertue and Perſonal Merits guide thoſe Sentiments of Reſpect and Veneration which you think is <hi>owing them.</hi> Among ſeveral Reaſons which perſwade me to give you this Advice, I will here lay down <hi>ſome</hi> of the moſt <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt of all, conſider this as a Truth, that although among <hi>Great Perſons</hi> there may be found ſome, whoſe Inclinations and Conduct <hi>anſwer exactly</hi> to their Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, the Number is infinitely the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er that <hi>derogates from</hi> it. Remember that they are for the moſt part like the Trees in Forreſts, which <hi>ſometimes</hi> yield Shade, but <hi>very rarely</hi> any Fruit; unleſs it be
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:133315:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>like thoſe Trees near the <hi>Dead Sea</hi> in the <hi>Holy Land,</hi> which proffer very <hi>fair Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> to Paſſengers, but within ſide are nothing but <hi>Dust</hi> and <hi>Rottenneſs.</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all the <hi>Great ones</hi> entice us after the ſame manner, oblige and gain us with large Promiſes, and by an exceſs of Civility, whereby we are too often caught; and never undeceiv'd, till an unhappy Experience in our Neceſſities convinceth us how little Reaſon we have to relye upon the Hopes or Expectations of what they promiſe. Beſides, if you <hi>ſhould</hi> be ſo fortunate as to be favour'd by ſome <hi>Great Perſon,</hi> (which will ſcarce happen unleſs his own Intereſt <hi>forceth</hi> him to it) in a ſmall time you will begin to perceive, that his Friendſhip has not only the falſe <hi>glittering</hi> of Glaſs, but alſo it's <hi>Brittleneſs;</hi> for generally the <hi>least Overſight</hi> makes them forget the <hi>greatest Service:</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, if you will be perſuaded by me, make no Addreſſes to <hi>Great Perſons</hi> or ſo much as come at them, unleſs you are obliged to it by a Duty not to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens'd with.</p>
               <p>Behave your ſelf with great Reſpect towards your Superiours, with civill
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:133315:46"/>Compliance among your equals, and always courteouſly towards your In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriours.</p>
               <p>Take heed how you ſpeak ill of any one, <hi>eſpecially in his Abſence?</hi> there is <hi>nothing</hi> more unworthy of a Man of Honour; and you will be ſo far from living in Peace with others, (which is the chief end of Society,) that of Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity you will be at odds with all. If you have privately perceiv'd the vicious Inclinations of any Perſon of your Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, do not <hi>Publiſh,</hi> but rather <hi>forget</hi> them, after you have done your utmoſt Endeavour to <hi>cure</hi> him of his Faults.</p>
               <p>One of the moſt conſiderable Services that we can render to a Neighbour is, to make him perceive the <hi>Errours</hi> of his <hi>Conduct:</hi> And to do this ſucceſsfully, ſo that he may ſee 'tis the Advice of a Friend; let Prudence guide you, leaſt he diſdain your Counſel inſtead of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiting thereby.</p>
               <p>You would become ridiculous, if <hi>you</hi> ſhould be ſtain'd with the <hi>ſame Vice</hi> which you reprove in <hi>another,</hi> and you will ſooner paſs for an impertinent <hi>Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer</hi>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:133315:47"/>than a ſincere <hi>Friend:</hi> Take heed therefore to that, and mend that Fault in <hi>your ſelf</hi> which you intend to cure in <hi>your Neighbour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Avoid the Baſeneſs of <hi>thoſe</hi> who delight in raiſing falſe Reports; and hearken not to <hi>thoſe</hi> who go about to ſcandalize others; If you do, you ſeek thereby an Occaſion to <hi>fall out</hi> with your <hi>Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour;</hi> and if you your ſelf create a Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal upon him, it will be a ſufficient Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for his <hi>falling out</hi> with <hi>you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Never praiſe <hi>to an Exceſs</hi> thoſe of whom you ſpeak, eſpecially if they are <hi>preſent,</hi> for altho 'tis but what they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, yet in <hi>their</hi> very Opinion you will be eſteem'd <hi>a Flatterer,</hi> ſuſpecting that the Intent of ſuch exceſſive Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations is <hi>more</hi> to exhibit the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancy of <hi>your Wit,</hi> than to manifeſt the Greatneſs of <hi>their Merit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Civility</hi> and <hi>Complaiſance</hi> are the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits that keep up Society, whoſoever is void of <hi>theſe</hi> is a trouble to all the World; whereas he that can make uſe of them opportunely, may <hi>boldly</hi> flatter himſelf that his Company will be unacceptable
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:133315:47"/>to <hi>none.</hi> However, let <hi>Reaſon</hi> rule your <hi>Com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>laiſance;</hi> let it not condeſcend to what is <hi>criminal,</hi> nor yet to what is <hi>baſe. Stubbornneſs</hi> is not only a deadly <hi>Enemy</hi> to <hi>Complaiſance,</hi> but it alſo acts for the moſt part contrary to <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Sence.</hi> A Perſon that is ſtubborn can never be ſo happy as to comply with others, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he falls into the Misfortune of being ſhun'd by all company, and at laſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes a Burden to himſelf. Endeavour therefore to be complaiſant with <hi>Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> and firm in your Reſolutions with <hi>Juſtice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jeer No body,</hi> if you would not run the Hazard of <hi>being jeer'd</hi> in your turn, and rendering that Perſon whom you jeer, <hi>your Enemy:</hi> Not but that innocent jeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing may be lawfully uſed in Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but the <hi>Abuſe</hi> of it doth not ſeldom produce Quarrels and Animoſities, which too often cool the moſt fervent Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and <hi>rarely</hi> do we ſee Raillery carry'd on without ſome ſharp, and ſtinging Expreſſions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Never put off</hi> till to morrow what you can do to day. Be exact towards all Men, and in all things, but principally
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:133315:48"/>in <hi>paying your Debts.</hi> Obſerve your meaſures ſo rightly, that the Preſence of your Creditors may not be tedious to you; and be always more ready to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade every Man <hi>to take</hi> his Due, than they <hi>to ask</hi> it of you. In the mean time do not you <hi>exact</hi> with the utmoſt Seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity what is due to you: This would be contrary to the Religion of JESUS CHRIST, as alſo not conſiſtent with that <hi>Civility</hi> and <hi>Condeſcenſion</hi> which we ow to one another.</p>
               <p>How deform'd ſoever any Perſon may be in his <hi>Body,</hi> be ſure that you have a great Care not to make it a <hi>Subject</hi> of <hi>Deriſion</hi> and <hi>Laughter;</hi> but rather render thanks to <hi>God,</hi> that he has bin pleas'd to favour you more then <hi>him.</hi> 'Tis out of his pure goodneſs that he has given you all thoſe <hi>Advantages</hi> of <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Mind</hi> which you poſſeſs; Why then ſhould you boaſt of what has bin given you undeſervedly? The more you have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, the more you have to anſwer for.</p>
               <p>Here, <hi>my Son,</hi> I bring you another ſort of Neighbour, your <hi>Domeſtick Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant:</hi> I would not have you think, that
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:133315:48"/>his Quality can diſcharge you from your <hi>Duty</hi> towards him. The <hi>chiefeſt part</hi> of your Duty, is to let your Carriage to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him be mild and eaſie, whereby, mitigating the Diſcontent which his hard Fortune might have rais'd in him; he may be induc'd to ſerve you joyfully: which if you deſire; <hi>recede</hi> ſo far from the Right of a Maſter as to come with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Bounds which Chriſtianity pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes, that is, conſider him as a <hi>Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> in <hi>God;</hi> behave your ſelf towards him as ſuch, and then you need not queſtion but he will become ſenſible of your Kindneſs. <hi>St. Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>forbear Threatning:</hi> How much more ought we to forbear <hi>Blows:</hi> Yet whenſoever he gives you a juſt Cauſe of Anger, be not <hi>too apt</hi> to liſten to thoſe Reaſons which condemn him; let him rather have cauſe to <hi>praiſe</hi> your <hi>Forbearance,</hi> than to <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain</hi> of your <hi>Rigour. Seneca</hi> ſaith; if we intend to gain our Servants ſo far, as to make them be entirely devoted to our Service, we muſt behave our ſelves to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them with all Mildneſs and Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarity. Make trial of this Counſel, and if (when all's done) your Servants become
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:133315:49"/>not more punctual in performing <hi>their Duty,</hi> (you having omitted no part of <hi>yours</hi> which might tend to their Satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,) diſmiſs them quietly, without <hi>Anger</hi> and without <hi>Noiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I cannot ſay, <hi>my Son,</hi> whether I have not forgot ſome conſiderable Point touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your <hi>Duty</hi> to your <hi>Neighbour;</hi> how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, if it were ſo, I have this Comfort left, That if you do juſtly put in Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice my Inſtructions upon this Subject, your Neighbour will have <hi>no great Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> to complain of you. It would tho be a Cauſe ſufficient for you to complain of me, if I ſhould conclude theſe Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons deſign'd for the Conduct of your <hi>Life,</hi> without making you ſenſible that nothing in the World can ſo much faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litate the Means to practiſe them, as fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent and ſerious Meditations on <hi>Death.</hi> I do confeſs, 'tis of all things the moſt terrible, eſpecially if we behold it in our <hi>Worldly Thoughts;</hi> for then it is more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to precipitate us into Deſpair than to inſpire us with the Love of Vertue and Piety. But it is far from being ſo full of Terrour to thoſe who behold it with the <hi>Eyes</hi> of Faith. This Divine Vertue, which
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:133315:49"/>is a true Character of a Chriſtian, makes <hi>Death</hi> appear to us already conquer'd and diſarm'd by the <hi>Second Adam,</hi> and ſent by him himſelf, as a welcome Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to open our Priſons upon Earth, and introduce us into a Celeſtial and Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Liberty. 'Tis true, in a State ſo cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt and imperfect wherein we now are, I believe it is a hard matter for the moſt Regenerate to ſuffer the <hi>Approaches</hi> of <hi>Death</hi> without ſome kind of Fear. But if once you can force your Weakneſs to admit of a Familiarity with <hi>Death;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Joy and Comfort you will reap from thence, it will change that familiar Habitude into a ſecond Nature; and then inſtead of thoſe <hi>vicious</hi> and <hi>corrupt Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations</hi> wherein you are born according to the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> it will inſpire ſuch as are truly <hi>vertuous,</hi> which will be the Signs as well as the Effects of your <hi>Spiritual Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration. My Son,</hi> be ſure you do not procraſtinate this Meditation, under the Pretext that you are as yet very young. A <hi>Glaſs</hi> newly blown is <hi>not a Jot</hi> leſs brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle than one that has been made ſeveral Years. A new <hi>Ship</hi> may be ſplit againſt the Rocks as ſoon as an <hi>old one:</hi> and how
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:133315:50"/>can you tell? Perhaps that <hi>very Minute</hi> which you employ to drive out of your Mind the <hi>Thoughts</hi> of <hi>Death,</hi> ſhall be your <hi>last</hi> in this World. Since therefore this Thing is of ſuch moment, and yet ſo uncertain, be always prepar'd. <hi>Watch and pray, for ye know not at what Hour the Lord cometh.</hi> Repent the Day before you die; and as there is no Day in your Life which may not be <hi>that</hi> of your Death, let not ſo much as <hi>one</hi> ſlip with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out throughly Repenting. Live juſt as you will wiſh to have liv'd when you are at the <hi>Point</hi> of <hi>Death,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly, ſoberly,</hi> and <hi>juſtly.</hi> This will not only have ſome Reſemblance with the <hi>three</hi> Bleſſings I mentioned at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this Treatiſe, upon your <hi>Soul,</hi> your <hi>Perſon,</hi> and your <hi>Actions;</hi> but alſo 'twill be a Teſtimony irrefragable that you have perform'd the <hi>three</hi> Duties which I preſcrib'd to you; for you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not live <hi>religiouſly,</hi> without doing your <hi>Duty</hi> towards <hi>God;</hi> nor <hi>ſoberly,</hi> without obſerving what is <hi>due</hi> to <hi>your ſelf;</hi> nor <hi>juſtly,</hi> without diſcharging what you owe to your <hi>Neighbour.</hi> The Father of Grace and Mercy grant that you may fulfill my
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:133315:50"/>Directions as a good Chriſtian, for the ſake of his Glory, your Salvation, and the Edification of your Neighbour.</p>
               <p>That you may conſider and meditate upon theſe Inſtructions with more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, and render them more familiar and ready to your <hi>Memory,</hi> I have extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted the choiceſt Matter, and reduc'd it under Heads more compact; whereby it will make the <hi>deeper Impreſſion</hi> upon your <hi>Mind.</hi> You will find it in the <hi>Maxims following,</hi> in all a hundred, which <hi>as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times</hi> would I have you read over, that you may be ſenſible how important they are, and conſequently how neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the <hi>Practice</hi> of them. Believe this, <hi>my Son,</hi> that whatſoever you can expect from me beſides, it cannot come near the Worth of theſe Inſtructions. <hi>God</hi> preſerve you, proſper your Voyage, and bring you back in all Happineſs. To conclude, <hi>my Son,</hi> let the <hi>Fear</hi> of <hi>God</hi> be the <hi>Star</hi> to lead and guide you in all your Ways; let it be the <hi>Center</hi> whereto all your Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons tend; and let it be the ſole <hi>Object</hi> of your Meditation.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="maxims">
            <pb n="86" facs="tcp:133315:51"/>
            <head>Chriſtian and Moral MAXIMES.</head>
            <p n="1">I. BE devout without Affectation: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of ſeeming ſo if you are not, for that is Hypocriſie; which being di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly againſt God, is a kind of Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege.</p>
            <p n="2">II. He that goes about to diſguiſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in the ſight of God, takes Pains to cheat himſelf.</p>
            <p n="3">III. To pray to God without Attenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is to pray without Hope.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. He that prefers the Pleaſures of his Body before the Salvation of his Soul, ſuffers a Man to be drowned whilſt he runs to ſave his Cloak.</p>
            <p n="5">V. If you have not more care to adorn your Soul with vertuous Qualities than to adorn your Body with fine Cloaths, you offer to an Idol and abandon God.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. He that delights in his Sins makes his Pleaſures his Executioner.</p>
            <pb n="87" facs="tcp:133315:51"/>
            <p n="7">VII. An habitual Sin is a Serpent nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed in their own Boſome.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. He that goes ſlowly in the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of good Works runs ſwiftly in the way to Hell.</p>
            <p n="9">IX. If you would have God hear your Requeſts, do you hear the Prayers of the Needy.</p>
            <p n="10">X. He that is afraid to think of Death will run into Deſpair when Death comes.</p>
            <p n="11">XI. There is no better School for a good Life than the frequent meditating upon a Holy Death.</p>
            <p n="12">XII. A ſerious Meditation of Eternity will cauſe you to make good uſe of your Time, and will take away the greateſt part of the bitterneſs of Death.</p>
            <p n="13">XIII. A Man is not fully convinced of the Importance of his own Salvation, when he knows his Sins and yet will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer his Repentance.</p>
            <p n="14">XIV. He that paſſeth his Life without Devotion ſhall not end it without De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair.</p>
            <p n="15">XV. If in your Proſperity you will not hear the Voice of God, you may well fear, that in your Adverſity he will not hear yours.</p>
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:133315:52"/>
            <p n="16">XVI. He that hath no fear of God in this Life may well fear his Judgments in the next Life.</p>
            <p n="17">XVII. Be obliging towards all men, familiar with a few, but be intimate with no more than one alone.</p>
            <p n="18">XVIII. He that takes Pleaſure to keep Company with naughty men, is in Pain whilſt he is among the good.</p>
            <p n="19">XIX. He that confides without Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, will repent not without Reaſon.</p>
            <p n="20">XX. He that begins a Buſineſs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Judgment need not wonder if it ends without Succeſs.</p>
            <p n="21">XXI. That which you undertake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove your Strength muſt needs produce Effects below your Hopes.</p>
            <p n="22">XXII. In a glorious Undertaking, he that is diſcouraged by the bare Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation of the Difficulties, neither under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands the value of the Honour, nor doth he at all deſerve it.</p>
            <p n="23">XXIII. If Haſte in deſigning, and Slowneſs in executing, produce good Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, it is by more chance.</p>
            <p n="24">XXIV. If you make your Work a trouble to you, you will make your Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty a Puniſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ment to you.</p>
            <pb n="89" facs="tcp:133315:52"/>
            <p n="25">XXV. He that in a low Fortune hath too high Deſigns, undertakes with wax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en Wings to fly up to the Sun.</p>
            <p n="26">XXVI. He that falls by aſpiring too high, needs not ſeek for any other Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his Fall than his own Extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance.</p>
            <p n="27">XXVII. Thoſe who ſhew themſelves over-earneſt and eager in ſmall Buſineſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, declare their Unfitneſs for great ones.</p>
            <p n="28">XXVIII. If by Juſtice you are guided in the purſuit of Gain, Tranquillity ſhall accompany you in the enjoyment there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
            <p n="29">XXIX. If with an envious Eye you look upon the Good of others, you will render your ſelf unworthy to poſſeſs your own.</p>
            <p n="30">XXX. If the Soul be given to Man only for Action, and thoſe who by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual Sloth keep the Soul from Acting, they ſhew that the Soul in their Bodies is but like a little Salt to preſerve their Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies from putrifying.</p>
            <p n="31">XXXI. Pride is a ſwelling of the Spirit, which doth as much corrupt all the good qualifications of the proud
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:133315:53"/>Man, as the ſwelling of the Stomack al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters the good humors of the Body.</p>
            <p n="32">XXXII. Altho Anger be but a ſhort Madneſs, yet the Effects thereof many times prove long Follies.</p>
            <p n="33">XXXIII. Avoid great Meals if you will avoid long Sickneſſes.</p>
            <p n="34">XXXIV. He that ſpoyls his health by Exceſſes and Diſorder, hath no Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to complain of the Exceſs of his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers.</p>
            <p n="35">XXXV. An able Cook is more to be feared in time of Health, than an igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Phyſician in time of Sickneſs.</p>
            <p n="36">XXXVI. Temperance and Exerciſe are the beſt Cooks in the world.</p>
            <p n="37">XXXVII. The Fumes of Wine trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles the Brain, the Fumes of Pride trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles the Underſtanding, and the Fumes of one in Love troubles both.</p>
            <p n="38">XXXVIII. He that fills his Heart with the Love of Women, turns a Sanctuary appointed for the Holy Ghoſt into a Temple of Idols, the Worſhip whereof will lead to Hell.</p>
            <p n="39">XXXIX. Divine Love is a Torch to light us; but profane Love is one to blind us.</p>
            <pb n="91" facs="tcp:133315:53" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="40">XL. Humane Love cannot have Bounds too ſtraight; but if Divine Love be at all bounded it will be deficient.</p>
            <p n="41">XLI. Love is painted naked; not only to repreſent Impudence, but to advertiſe us, that uſually it ſtrips naked all thoſe who follow it.</p>
            <p n="42">XLII. The Covetous Man ſpares things neceſſary to provide Superfluities for thoſe who will never thank him for them.</p>
            <p n="43">XLIII. Thoſe who in their Actings conſult only ſelf Love ſhall walk blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold, and have as many Falls as Steps.</p>
            <p n="44">XLIV. Who ſpends too much upon his Pleaſures; deprives himſelf of the Means of providing for Neceſſaries.</p>
            <p n="45">XLV. If you ſubmit your Judgment to your Pleaſures, you will Burn your ſelf with the Light which was given to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect you.</p>
            <p n="46">XLVI. He that conſults not his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for his Pleaſures, ought not to expect help in his pains.</p>
            <p n="47">XLVII. He that ſuffers himſelf to be governed by his Paſſions, abandons his Liberty to the Fancy of his Slaves.</p>
            <pb n="92" facs="tcp:133315:54"/>
            <p n="48">XLVIII. Too great deſire after things Superfluous oft throws a Man into ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme want of Neceſſaries.</p>
            <p n="49">XLIX. He that fills his Heart with his Paſſions leaves no room for Piety, and changes his condition of Chriſtian into that of an Idolater.</p>
            <p n="50">L. Since Paſſions are the Diſeaſes of the Soul, nothing but Temperance is fit to be the Phyſician.</p>
            <p n="51">LI. He that exceſſively delights in Play, muſt count that he ſhall dye in Poverty.</p>
            <p n="52">LII. Winning at Play is the Bait which Fortune makes uſe of to undo us.</p>
            <p n="53">LIII. Thoſe who Play to recover what they have loſt, add to the loſs of their Money, the loſs of their Reaſon, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten times the loſs of the reſt of their Money.</p>
            <p n="54">LIV. Much Sleep and much Play fill the Stomach with Crudities, and the Purſe with Wind.</p>
            <p n="55">LV. Think a little before you Speak, think more before you make a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe.</p>
            <pb n="93" facs="tcp:133315:54"/>
            <p n="56">LVI. In divers affairs you may chooſe if you will make a Promiſe, but having made a Promiſe you cannot diſpenſe therewith.</p>
            <p n="57">LVII. Never diſcourſe of things where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of you are ignorant, and diſcourſe but little of what you know, and whether you ſpeak or are ſilent do all with diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion.</p>
            <p n="58">LVIII. Jeſting ſometimes upholds Converſation but generally diſunites the Jeſters. They that deſire to avoid quarrels and live in quiet let them avoid Jeſting as a Snare.</p>
            <p n="59">LIX. If you do not eaſily bear with the failings of others you will render your own failings unſufferable.</p>
            <p n="60">LX. He that careleſsly regards the misfortunes of other Men, ought not to think it ſtrainge if others look upon his misfortunes without compaſſion.</p>
            <p n="61">LXI. If you think to oblige Men to be civil and courteous towards you, give them Example by your carriage towards them.</p>
            <p n="62">LXII. The Favors which you do to other Men place under your Feet, the Favours
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:133315:55"/>which others do to you place at your Heart.</p>
            <p n="63">LXIII. He that forgets favours recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved deſerves no more.</p>
            <p n="64">LXIV. Be not ſlow in ſerving others if you would have them quick in doing Pleaſures to you.</p>
            <p n="65">LXV. If you are not generous enough to prevent your Friend by good Turns, be not ſlow to requite his to you.</p>
            <p n="66">LXVI. A ſincere Intention, although unprofitable, better repays a good Turn than a forced Acknowledgment.</p>
            <p n="67">LXVII. He that brags of a Favour that he hath done, doth much diminiſh the merit thereof; for by his Indiſcretion he makes it appear, that he is divided betwixt his Vain-glory and his Friend.</p>
            <p n="68">LXVIII. He that gives to receive, of a generous Act (which is one of the moſt commendable Qualities of a man of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour) makes it to be one of the moſt dirty Trades in the World.</p>
            <p n="69">LXIX. If you take Pleaſure in Lies, Truth will become a Pain to you.</p>
            <p n="70">LXX. He that excuſeth his Fault by a Lye condemns himſelf two ways.</p>
            <pb n="95" facs="tcp:133315:55"/>
            <p n="71">LXXI. If Lying be uſual with you, you miſtruſt all that others tell you.</p>
            <p n="72">LXXII. He that makes uſe of Cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and Lying to get his Neighbours Goods, imitates the Devil, who made uſe of both thoſe Qualities to rob our firſt Parent of his Innocence.</p>
            <p n="73">LXXIII. The ill uſing of our Goods in this World will be one of the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal and moſt juſt cauſe of our miſery in the next.</p>
            <p n="74">LXXIV. He that is not content with a moderate Fortune, oft times takes great Pains to leſſen it by endeavouring to aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it.</p>
            <p n="75">LXXV. He that regulates his Deſires by the neceſſities of Nature, aims but at a few things; but he that is led by his Luſt gives no Bounds to his Deſires.</p>
            <p n="76">LXXVI. Be not eager to know other Mens Secrets. Be very reſerved in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating your own; you are no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Maſter of them ſo ſoon as you have imparted them to any Perſon; and your Example ſeems to juſtifie his Unfaithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in diſcovering them to a third Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
            <pb n="96" facs="tcp:133315:56"/>
            <p n="77">LXXVII. He that boaſts of his good Qualities, loſes the merit of them by his Pride; and he that hides his good Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, gives them a higher eſteem by his Modeſty.</p>
            <p n="78">LXXVIII. High Places make their Heads turn who have but weak Brains, and extraordinary Fortunes trouble the Spirit of thoſe who have not good Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p n="79">LXXIX. A Man hath need of great Conſtancy in Adverſity, that he may not be wanting to himſelf, and of great Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration in Proſperity, that he may not be wanting to others.</p>
            <p n="80">LXXX. Proſperity makes others know truly what we are, and Adverſity makes us know who are our true Friends.</p>
            <p n="81">LXXXI. Thoſe who haunt us for our Wealth are like Hawks that fly only for the Prey.</p>
            <p n="82">LXXXII. He that will not know his Friends in his Proſperity deſerves to meet with none in his Miſery.</p>
            <p n="83">LXXXIII. He that leans over-much on the Friendſhip of Great Perſons, will find, ſooner or later, that he leans upon a broken Reed.</p>
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:133315:56"/>
            <p n="84">LXXXIV. God by his extreme Boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty recompenſes with extraordinary Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours the leaſt Duties which we render to him, but the moſt part of great Perſons who are earthly Gods, make account that they have over rewarded our great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Services by a few kind Words.</p>
            <p n="85">LXXXV. He that takes great care to preſerve the friendſhip of great Men, ſhall know when he hath need of them, that he hath taken much pains to culti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Land that will prove barren.</p>
            <p n="86">LXXXVI. A Man who hath excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Parts and great Learning yet makes no uſe thereof; is like a good Sword ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver drawn out of the Scabbard.</p>
            <p n="87">LXXXVII. He that adviſes others to be vertuous hath thereby the more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to be ſo himſelf.</p>
            <p n="88">LXXXVIII. He that praiſes and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends only to pleaſe his complaiſance, draws his judgment in queſtion.</p>
            <p n="89">LXXXIX. The forwardlyneſs of a Man to adviſe others is oftner a mark of his Preſumption then a proof of his Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</p>
            <p n="90">XC. He that thinks it enough to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wail our Evils when he can Cure them,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:133315:57"/>is not toucht at the Heart, but ſheds only Crocodiles tears.</p>
            <p n="91">XCI. In our great diſpleaſures our firſt Tears may be juſt, the ſecond may be handſome, but thoſe after that are nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reaſonable nor honorable.</p>
            <p n="92">XCII. He that weeps only becauſe he thinks he ought to weep may have tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Eyes and yet not toucht at the Heart.</p>
            <p n="93">XCIII. He that employes his Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to do ill things or to maintain them, cuts his Throat with his own Knife.</p>
            <p n="94">XCIV. Truſt not Flatterers and great Talkers, both of them uſually aim by the wind of their words to drive thy Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney out of thy Purſe.</p>
            <p n="95">XCV. Phyſicians by their Medicines oft Poyſon our Bodies, and Flatterers al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways Poyſon our minds by their Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes.</p>
            <p n="96">XCVI. He that makes uſe of a much ſtudied Diſcourſe to perſwade us to an evil Deſign, employes a perfumed Pony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard to ſtab us at the heart.</p>
            <p n="97">XCVII. The infection of the Peſtilence is not ſo much to be feared for the Body as the Poyſon of evil Company for the Mind.</p>
            <pb n="99" facs="tcp:133315:57"/>
            <p n="98">XCVIII. If you deſire to dye like a righteous Man, live as a Reprobate would wiſh to have lived when he comes to dye.</p>
            <p n="99">XCIX. He that by his extraordinary complaiſance draws off his Friend from a bad Buſineſs by being Surety for him or bayling of him, uſually draws himſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a worſe Buſineſs, which at length will make him underſtand his own want of Judgment.</p>
            <p n="100">C. He that reads for his own inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and reads good matters without profiting thereby, hath the taſt of the Mind as much depraved, as the bodily Taſt is to a ſick Man who ſits at a well furniſht Table and not able to eat.</p>
            <p>My Son, I having at the beginning of theſe Inſtructions made uſe of one of the Proverbs of Solomon, I will make uſe of another for the end. 3 Prov. 1, 2, 3, and 4 ver: <hi>My Son, forget not my Law, but let thine heart keep my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, for length of Days, and long Life, and Peace ſhall they add to thee, ſo ſhalt thou find favour and good underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the ſight of God and Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:133315:58"/>
            <head>Books <hi>Printed for</hi> William Crook, <hi>Bookseller, at the Sign of the</hi> Green Dragon <hi>without</hi> Temple Bar, <hi>nigh the Paſſage into the</hi> Temple, <hi>by</hi> Devereux Court, 1683.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>DIVINITY.</head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>BRevis Demonstratio,</hi> being the truth of the Chriſtian Religion, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by Reaſon, 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. price bound 10 <hi>d.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>The Primitive Inſtitution,</hi> ſhewing the antiquity and uſefulneſs of Catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing, together with its ſuitableneſs to heal the diſtempers of the Church, by <hi>L. Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſon,</hi> D.D. price 1 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. A <hi>Sermon</hi> preached at the <hi>Funeral</hi> of a ſober Religious Man, found drown'd in a Pit, in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. price bound 1 <hi>s.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Mr. <hi>Howel</hi>'s Viſitation Sermon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Biſhop of <hi>Chicheſter,</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. price 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Dr. <hi>Haſcard</hi>'s two Sermons on the 5th of <hi>November,</hi> and the other before the L. Mayor of <hi>London,</hi> in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:133315:58"/>
               <p n="6">6. Mr. <hi>Manningham</hi>'s two Sermons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the L. Mayor of <hi>London,</hi> and at St. <hi>Mari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> in <hi>Oxford.</hi> in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
               <p n="7">7. A <hi>Sermon</hi> preached at the <hi>Savoy</hi> in <hi>French,</hi> and ſince printed in <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Engliſh.</hi> 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. price bound 8 <hi>d.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>A modeſt Plea for the Clergy,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is conſidered the reaſons why the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy are ſo contemned and neglected. By <hi>L. A.</hi> D. D. price 1 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. <hi>Hugo Grotius</hi> his <hi>Catechiſm, Greek, Latin,</hi> and <hi>Engliſh;</hi> with a <hi>Praxis</hi> of all the <hi>Greek</hi> words therein contained, in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. price bound 2 <hi>s.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>The Spirit of Prophecy,</hi> proving, that Chriſt and his Apoſtles were Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets: written by the direction of, and recommended to the Preſs, by the Right reverend Father in God, <hi>Peter,</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Ely,</hi> in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. price 3 <hi>s.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. <hi>The King-Killing Doctrine of the Jeſuites,</hi> in a ſincere diſcourſe to the <hi>French</hi> King: written by a <hi>Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick,</hi> in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. price 1 <hi>s.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="12">12. <hi>Juſtifying Faith;</hi> with the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the <hi>Common Prayer Book,</hi> in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. price bound 1 <hi>s.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="13">13. <hi>Mercy Triumphant,</hi> or the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Chriſt enlarged beyond the nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row
<pb facs="tcp:133315:59"/>bounds which have been wont to be ſet to it. By <hi>Ed. Lane.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="14">14. <hi>Du Moulin</hi>'s <hi>Reflections reverbera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi> being a full anſwer to the damning Doctrine of Dr. <hi>Lewis Du Moulin:</hi> alſo, a Confutation of <hi>Edmund Hickeringill</hi>'s railing againſt the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Courts.</hi> By <hi>E. Lane,</hi> in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Price 1 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="15">15. <hi>Reſponſio Valedictoria ad ſecundam</hi> Sandii <hi>Epistolam, &amp;c. per</hi> Sam. Gardiner, S. T. D. in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. price 1 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="16">16. Introductions to the Sacrament, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more eaſy and plain Rules for the Holy Communion than any yet Extant. By <hi>L. Addiſon, Dean</hi> of Lichfield; price 6 <hi>d.</hi>bound.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>LAW.</head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>THE Juriſdiction of the Authority of</hi> Court-Leets, Court Barons, Court Marſhalſea, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> together with the moſt neceſſary learning of <hi>Tenures,</hi> and all their Incidents of <hi>Eſſoyns, &amp;c.</hi> with the <hi>Return</hi> and <hi>Forms</hi> of ſeveral Original and Judicial <hi>Writs,</hi> now in uſe, relating to <hi>Writs</hi> of Error, <hi>Writs</hi> of falſe Judgment, and other proceedings of frequent uſe in the <hi>Courts of Westminſter:</hi> by <hi>J. Kitchen</hi> of <hi>Grays Inn</hi> Eſq To which is added <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>via
<pb facs="tcp:133315:59"/>ſelecta,</hi> being a choice Collection of Special <hi>Writs;</hi> the fifth Edition, in <hi>octavo.</hi> price 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Praxis Curiae Admiralitatis Angliae,</hi> Author <hi>Francis Clarke,</hi> in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. price 1 <hi>s.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>The Reports</hi> of Sir <hi>Henry Hobart,</hi> Chief Juſtice of the Common Pleas, <hi>folio.</hi> price 10 <hi>s.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Formulae bene placitandi,</hi> a Book of Entries, containing Variety of Choice Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedents: by <hi>W. Brown,</hi> in two Parts, <hi>folio.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>The</hi> 2, 3, <hi>and</hi> 4th. <hi>Parts of the Inſtitutes of the Laws of</hi> England; by Sir <hi>Ed. Coke, folio.</hi> price 30 <hi>s.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Officina Brevium:</hi> Select and approved Forms of Judicial Writs, and other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, with their Returns and Entries in the Court of <hi>Common Pleas:</hi> as alſo Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial pleadings to Writs, <hi>folio.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Young Clark</hi>'s <hi>Guide,</hi> in four parts, or an exact Collection of choice Engliſh Preſidents, octavo.</p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>A Dialogue betwixt a</hi> Student <hi>and a</hi> Philoſopher <hi>about the</hi> Common Law <hi>of</hi> England; by <hi>Thomas Hobs</hi> of <hi>Malm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bury,</hi> in octavo.</p>
               <p n="9">9. The Reports in the <hi>Kings Bench, Checquer,</hi> and <hi>Common Pleas,</hi> by the late
<pb facs="tcp:133315:60"/>Lord <hi>Keeper Littleton,</hi> in <hi>folio;</hi> printed 1683, not one Caſe printed in any other Book of Reports: price 12 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. The Compleat Sollicitor, Entring Clark, and Attorney, fully inſtructed in the Practice, Methods, and Clarkſhip of all his Majeſties Courts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 1683.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>HISTORY.</head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>AN Inſtitution of general Hiſtory,</hi> or the Hiſtory of the World; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a compleat body thereof, in two Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes, by <hi>W. Howel,</hi> now Chancellor of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> in <hi>folio.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Hiſtorical Collections,</hi> being an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the Proceedings of the four laſt Parliaments of Qu. <hi>Elizab.</hi> by <hi>H. Town<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end</hi> Eſq; in <hi>folio.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Scarron<hi>'s Comical Romance,</hi> being an Hiſtorical account of a company of <hi>Stage-Players,</hi> full of variety of <hi>Novels,</hi> rare <hi>Adventures,</hi> amorous <hi>Intreagues,</hi> &amp;c. being both witty and pleaſant, in <hi>fol.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Popiſh Cruelties,</hi> being an account of the Treaſons of Dr. <hi>Purry</hi> againſt Qu. <hi>Eliz.</hi> with his Confeſſion of it at his Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, and his denyal at his Execution; <hi>folio,</hi> price 1 <hi>s.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>The Life</hi> of <hi>Thomas Hobbs</hi> of <hi>Malms<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:133315:60"/>written by himſelf in Latin; ſince tranſlated into <hi>Engliſh,</hi> in <hi>folio,</hi> price 6 d.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>An Hiſtorical Narration of Hereſy,</hi> with an account of the Puniſhments there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, by <hi>Tho. Hobbs</hi> of <hi>Malmsbury,</hi> in <hi>folio,</hi> price 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Megalopſichy,</hi> being a particular and exact account of the laſt 17 years of Qu. <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Reign, both <hi>Military</hi> and <hi>Civil;</hi> the firſt written by Sir <hi>W. Monſon,</hi> one of the ſaid Queens Admirals; the ſecond written by <hi>H. Townſend</hi> Eſq a Member of her laſt Parliament. Wherein is a true and faithful Relation of all the <hi>expediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> attempts, <hi>deſigns,</hi> ſucceſſes, and <hi>errors,</hi> both of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> in the Wars from the Year 1585, to the ſaid Queens Death. With a full account of the eminent <hi>Speeches</hi> and <hi>Debates,</hi> &amp;c. in the ſaid Time. To which is added, Dr. <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi>'s Tryal in the Year 1584. All written <hi>at the time of the Actions</hi> by Perſons that were <hi>eminently acting therein, folio,</hi> price bound 10 <hi>s.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>A Voyage into the Levant,</hi> being a Relation of a Journey lately performed from <hi>England</hi> to <hi>Grand Cairo,</hi> by Sir <hi>Hen. Blunt,</hi> 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. price 1 <hi>s.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:133315:61"/>
               <p n="9">9. <hi>A Diſcription of Candia,</hi> with an exact account of the laſt Siege and Surren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of it to the <hi>Turks,</hi> in octavo, price bound 1 <hi>s.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. A Diſcourſe of the <hi>Dukedom</hi> of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dena,</hi> containing the original Antiquity <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of that <hi>Dukedom,</hi> in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. price 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. <hi>The Travels of</hi> Ulyſſes, how he went to Hell and came back again, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by <hi>Tho. Hobbs,</hi> price 1 s.</p>
               <p n="12">12. <hi>The Preſent State of</hi> London, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the Antiquity, Fame, Walls, Rivers, Gates, Churches, Bridge, with the Cuſtoms and Infranchizements: by <hi>J. Bridal,</hi> Eſq. price 1 s.</p>
               <p n="13">13. <hi>The Life and Death of</hi> Mahomet, being the firſt eſtate of <hi>Mahometiſm,</hi> ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the deſigns that that Impoſtor <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet</hi> had to carry on and ſettle the <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh</hi> Religion; written by <hi>L. Addiſon,</hi> D.D. price 1 s. 6 d.</p>
               <p n="14">14. The <hi>Connexion,</hi> being Collections of ſome principal Matters in the Reign of King <hi>James,</hi> being the time that nothing of this Nature is printed, being betwixt the end of <hi>Megalopſichy,</hi> or the laſt ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen years of Qu. <hi>Elz.</hi> and the beginnings
<pb facs="tcp:133315:61"/>of Mr. <hi>Ruſhworth, Heath, Nalſon, Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock,</hi> and others, price 1 s. 6 d.</p>
               <p n="15">15. <hi>The</hi> Moors <hi>baffled,</hi> being a diſcourſe of the Government of <hi>Tangier,</hi> under the Earl of <hi>Tiviot;</hi> ſhewing the Subtilty and Policies of both Parties, written by Dr. <hi>Addiſon,</hi> who lived there many Years: price 6 d. 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
               <p>The whole Series of the Plot; being the Journal-book of the Houſe of Lords in the time of the laſt Popiſh Plot. 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
               <p n="17">17. <hi>All the Works of</hi> Homer, both <hi>Illiads</hi> and <hi>Oddyſes,</hi> tranſlated out of Greek in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Engliſh, by <hi>Tho. Hobbs</hi> of <hi>Malmsbury,</hi> price 5 s. 6. d.</p>
               <p n="18">18. <hi>Conſiderations</hi> on the Loyalty, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, Manners, and Reputation of <hi>Tho. Hobbs,</hi> 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. price bound 1 s.</p>
               <p n="19">19. The <hi>Memoires,</hi> and rare <hi>Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> of <hi>Henrietta Sylvia Moliere,</hi> a great Lady in <hi>France,</hi> now living: written <hi>by her ſelf,</hi> in ſix Parts, in <hi>French,</hi> and now tranſlated into <hi>Engliſh.</hi> price 4 s.</p>
               <p n="20">20. Tho. Hobbs <hi>Angli Malmsb. Vita,</hi> being an account of Mr. <hi>Hobbs,</hi> of the Books he wrote, of the Times when, and the occaſion thereof, of the Books and Authors againſt him, of his Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb facs="tcp:133315:62"/>Acquaintance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> part wrote by himſelf, the reſt by Dr. <hi>B.</hi> in octavo, printed 1681.</p>
               <p n="21">21. <hi>Behemoth,</hi> being the Hiſtory of the Civil Wars of <hi>England,</hi> and the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels and Artifices by which they were car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on from 1640 to 1660, printed now from his own perfect Copy, in which is many Pages more than was in the former <hi>Counterfeit Editions,</hi> none of which Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions before this, had leſs than <hi>a thouſand Faults</hi> in them, whole lines left out in a <hi>hundred Places,</hi> which did extreamly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the ſence of the Author <hi>Tho. Hobbs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="22">22. <hi>The Tracts</hi> of Mr. <hi>Tho. Hobbs</hi> of <hi>Malmsb.</hi> in 2 Vol. in oct. gathering <hi>Nine</hi> of his Treatiſes together, which are alſo to be had ſingle, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. <hi>His Life,</hi> in La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin. 2. His <hi>Conſiderations</hi> on his Loyalty, Religion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 3. His Art of <hi>Rhetorick,</hi> in <hi>Engliſh.</hi> 4. His Dialogue about the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law of</hi> England. 5. His ten Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logues of <hi>Natural Philoſophy.</hi> 6. His <hi>Civil Wars of</hi> England, the perfect Edition. 7. His Hiſtorical Narration of <hi>Hereſie.</hi> 8. His Anſwer to Biſhop <hi>Bramhal</hi> in <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of his Leviathan.</hi> 9. His ſeven Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blems, with an Apology for his Writings to the King, price bound 12 <hi>s.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:133315:62"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
